<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reformation not separation, or, Mr. Crofton's plea for communion with the church ... in a letter, written July 20, 1661 ... / by the said R.S. to whom it was written ; unto which, is added the copy of another letter, written on the same occasion and subject.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12032501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12032501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 865:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reformation not separation, or, Mr. Crofton's plea for communion with the church ... in a letter, written July 20, 1661 ... / by the said R.S. to whom it was written ; unto which, is added the copy of another letter, written on the same occasion and subject.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
                  <author>P. E., Reverend.</author>
                  <author>R. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>The second letter is written to the Rev. P.E., with his reply.</note>
                  <note>An appendix to the foregoing letter ...: p. [53].</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Zachary Crofton. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52790:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52790:1"/>
            <p>REFORMATION NOT SEPARATION: OR, Mr. CROFTON'S Plea for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the CHURCH, under thoſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and by that diſorderly Miniſtration to which he cannot Conform, nor by it Adminiſter.</p>
            <p>IN A LETTER, Written J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LY 20. 1661.</p>
            <p>In, and from the TOWER of <hi>LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON,</hi> to <hi>R. S.</hi> To ſatisfie the Weak, and ſilence the Wicked, who inſulted in, or were offended at his endeavoured (and clamorouſly reported as obtained) attendance on Gods PUBLICK WORSHIP in that Place, during his Confinement.</p>
            <p>NOW PUBLISHED, To ſilence Cenſures and Calumnies, ſatisfie ſuch who would walk uprightly in this houre of Temptation.</p>
            <p>By the ſaid <hi>R. S.</hi> to whom it was written.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unto which, is added the Copy of another</hi> LETTER, <hi>Written on the ſame Occaſion and Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the YEAR, M.DC.LXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52790:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is more than a Year, ſince it was clamoured, <hi>Mr. CROFTON goeth to the Church, and heareth Common-Prayer in the Tower of LONDON:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was not little Cenſured by ſome, whoſe Profeſſion of Religion, and Relation to him, required much more Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. CROFTON</hi> did then write unto me this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>LETTER,</hi> with Advice to Communicate the ſame, for the <hi>Satisfaction of the Weak,</hi> who ſtumbled (to their own wounding) and <hi>Silencing of the Wicked,</hi> who inſulted, to the Grief of him and Gods Church.</p>
            <p>In Obſervation of this Inſtruction, I did (to ſave the labour of the Pen, and make this Paper more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Church) put it into the Preſs; where ſome good Friends did ſeize, and for preſent ſtiſle it; chooſing rather to Communicate the written Copy as they could.</p>
            <p>This Copy was imparted to many Chriſtian Friends and Miniſters, who ſeemed to be in this matter otherwiſe perſwaded; in ſpecial, Thoſe of the <hi>Congregational way,</hi> who ſeemed moſt concerned in the ſame; theſe were all requeſted to Correct <hi>Mr. CROFTON'S</hi> Errour, and Rectifie his Judgment; but none would, or did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the work, though aſſured he had an hearing Ear: <hi>Horreſco referens;</hi> though he hath been moſt bitterly Cenſured, he never received any, the leaſt Admonition
<pb facs="tcp:52790:3"/>
concerning this matter, one excepted; a Copy whereof, with his Anſwer thereunto, being come to my hands, I have preſumed to annex unto this <hi>LETTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I preſume (without <hi>Mr. CROFTON'S</hi> knowledge)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To make theſe Papers publick, to <hi>evidence</hi> the little Cauſe men have to repreſent <hi>Mr. CROFTON'S Non-conforming Communion,</hi> to be a Defection from the Cauſe of Reformation, and Reſult of his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To let men ſee on what Grounds <hi>Mr. CROFTON</hi> hath ſatisfied himſelf in his ſolitary E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, when he could neither Confer with Men and Books; that ſo if they appear weak, ſome ſerious man, may by word or letter (whilſt the Preſs will not be allowed to ſpeak) help him to Conviction; I cannot but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it unchriſtian, to condemn without <hi>Fraternal Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption,</hi> or an Eſſay for Conviction; thoſe Cenſures do reflect with Violence on the Cenſurers, which are retorted with <hi>a what doth your arguing reprove?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To help others to diſcover that <hi>Point of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which is proper for their places and capacities, under the preſent Providences of God in, and towards his Church in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>What lately was <hi>Mr. CROFTON'S</hi> Caſe, is now our own; we muſt either <hi>withdraw</hi> from the Prayers and Publick Worſhip of God in this Church, or <hi>attend</hi> it by this <hi>diſguiſed Miniſterial Mode and Order;</hi> and with Grief I ſpeak it, we are in the dark, and we are left in the dark, our Prophets are gone, who ſhould tell us, and before their going have not told us, how in this Caſe Chriſtianity doth require us to carry: Some general Cautions we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed received in their laſt Councels, but no clear Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:52790:3"/>
in reference to the ſpecial Caſe and Condition into which we are reſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: I well know, moſt Presbyterian Divines to be in Judgment the ſame with <hi>Mr. CROFTON;</hi> but their Prudence doth prohibit the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof to us, or at leaſt in a particular Specification of our preſent Condition.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay, <hi>Mr. CROFTON</hi> by his Act or Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, appeareth any very wiſe Pilate, I leave thoſe to whom it doth belong, to judge his skill in the Compaſs; but I cannot but ſay, he ſeemeth to be moſt <hi>Simply Faithful,</hi> in fufilling his Miniſtry, propoſing himſelf a pattern, and perſwading his friends and people to walk in the <hi>Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Truth</hi> againſt all Extreams, though his worldly and carnal Intereſt lieth on either hand, and might eaſily induce him to advance, or at leaſt by his ſilence to abett the ſame. I cannot but obſerve this is not the firſt time <hi>Mr. CROFTON</hi> hath divided from the Policies of them who could not diſown his Principles, or Scripturally determine againſt his Practice: And truly I wiſh men may conſider, whether the <hi>Serpent</hi> do not out-ſtretch and over-reach the <hi>Dove,</hi> in thoſe Policies which make <hi>Religion</hi> (unto its reproach) a matter of Faction; and ſtudy to ſave, and recover <hi>Reformation,</hi> by the appearance of a Bulky Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for <hi>Separation?</hi> I cannot but let thee know, I am thus far clear of <hi>Mr. CROFTON'S</hi> mind, <hi>Unwarrantable Non-communion</hi> may not be allowed, no not for a day, though to ſaving Reformation; for we may not do Evil, that Good may come thereof; and I cannot be perſwaded, I am disbanded from Chriſts Army, ſo ſoon as I am ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded to my Conduct; I muſt march under his Banner, when I may not be permitted to march at the Head of a Company: And ſure I am, it is more eaſie to fall into ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:52790:4"/>
Extream, than to walk between both <hi>uprightly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Truth of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader;</hi> I will stay thee no longer, only know, That <hi>this Seaſon of Publication</hi> of this <hi>LETTER,</hi> is by me cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, or rather conſtrained by the over-prudent <hi>Superſedeas</hi> before mentioned, and <hi>ſilence</hi> our <hi>over-general Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of our pious Miniſters in this Caſe, and houre of <hi>Temptation</hi> which is come upon us.</p>
            <p>If any <hi>Miniſter</hi> be hereby provoked to beat out the Truth, which muſt guide the Churches Practice: If any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> do hereby receive Direction to diſpel his Doubts, and ſteer his Converſation: Or if any <hi>raſhly cenſorious Saint</hi> be hereby convinced of their unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, unchriſtian Cenſures, and bitter words; by which they have wounded themſelves, and grieved him whom God hath ſmitten, be hereby convinced of their fault, ſo as to give Glory to God, and with <hi>Jobs</hi> Comforters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their Guilts, I have obtained mine End, and hope it ſhall not much diſpleaſe my Paſtor, on whom, I confeſs, I have herein too much preſumed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am thine in Union with the Church, And Simplicity of the Goſpel.</hi> R. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. <hi>1. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52790:4"/>
                  <head>REFORMATION no SEPARATION: OR, <hi>Zachary Croftons</hi> Plea for Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> In a Letter to a Chriſtian Friend.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Chriſtian Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering we live in an Age exceeding ſcrupulous, and the actions of a Priſoner are ſubject to Obſervation and Cenſure, without the leaſt enquiry into the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, end and inducements thereof: And well knowing my unhappy ſelf to be a man much miſtaken and miſrepreſented; obnoxious to, and afflicted with the groundleſs calumnies of the wicked, and cenſures of the weak: And being deeply ſenſible of the ſad doom denounced againſt ſuch as adminiſter <hi>Offence to any of Chriſts little ones;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat 18.6.</note> and the great damage and danger of a groundleſs offence, choaking the joy, and curbing the duty of ſuch as take it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> (who have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52790:5"/>
for more then ſix moneths been buried alive) do conceive a duty and neceſſity incumbent upon me, to appear, and (by ſuch utenſils as a cloſe and ſevere impriſonment will afford) to ſpeak for my ſelf, in the cauſe of God and his Church (charged on my weak hands) in reference to an act, which Conſcience doth conſtrain me to purſue; and (or obtained liberty) to attend. In which I diſcern ſome ready to inſult, whileſt others ſoon ſcandalized, beyond what the nature thereof may occaſion, to the one or the other; for God (whom I ſerve in the Spirit) is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I would give no offence, neither to the Jew, nor to the Greek, nor to the Church of God.</p>
                  <p>The caſe is this:</p>
                  <p>SIr <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> the Lieutenant of the Tower, did of his own accord (not at that time, though often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, moved to it by or from me) on <hi>Fryday</hi> the thirteenth inſtant, ſend me word by my Keeper, <hi>That I ſhould have liberty to go to Church, and enjoy the Solemn Aſſembly, and Publique Worſhip of God, celebrated within this place</hi> (the which on ſecond thoughts he hath remanded;) in the uſe hereof, I muſt of neceſſity attend that Order of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, againſt which I have publiquely witneſſed, as that which is <hi>Corrupt and Superſtitious;</hi> yet conſcience of duty doth compel me to receive and uſe this liberty (when I can obtain it) as a mercy from God, and favour from men, the which I have often prayed for and deſired. Hereupon I apprehend a clamour is ſent abroad, that Mr. <hi>Crofton is preſent at, and attends unto the reading of the Service-Book;</hi> in which ſome <hi>boaſt</hi> beyond meaſure, as having gained a Proſelyte; whileſt others <hi>ſtumble,</hi> as if I ſtarted from the truth and work of Reformation, and teſtimony which (through Gods grace) I have given thereunto.</p>
                  <p>My good Friend, you muſt know, this clamour is <hi>(as to the fact)</hi> as yet falſe, the liberty being not yet obtained,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52790:5"/>
but I confined to my <hi>Solitary Sabbaths,;</hi> wherein I hope, I can profeſs, <hi>I am not alone,</hi> becauſe the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is with me: But indeed I muſt confeſs it true in (the <hi>fieri</hi>) my deſire, intention and endeavour to procure this liberty, ſo ſoon as I can, and my reſolution to attend thoſe corrupt Adminiſtrations, and this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſervice of God, until God pleaſe to bring me forth, and make me drink the waters of his Sanctuary in purer Veſſels; and I cannot but proteſt, that the one or the other, inſulting, or offended at my ſo doing, may grieve me, and wound their own ſouls, but cannot ſay they know me, who was ever ſatisfied (and ſo declared my ſelf in my publique Miniſtery) as to this point; or that I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter any cauſe for ſuch inſultation or offence: Yet to the end Gods diſhonor, Religions diſgrace, their own danger by this their ſin, may (if poſſible) be prevented, I thought it my duty to ſignifie to you, and require you (as you have opportunity) to communicate to others, theſe following conſiderations, as Apologetical reaſons, for what I am convinced, is not onely lawful, but a poſitive duty, not without ſin to be omitted, though the critiſim of our times, and my ſpecial caſe, may require an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My long, cloſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſid.</hi> 1. Deliberate thoughts, not diſtreſs of condition provoke it.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſevere durance</hi> (much beyond any other Priſoner in this place) <hi>or any carnal, ſelf, politique Principle,</hi> hath not been <hi>the impulſive cauſe</hi> of my deſire, or uſe of this liberty, but (as in my other acts, ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the cenſure of men) <hi>pure conſcience of duty</hi> towards God and my own ſoul, and the <hi>preponderate dictates of my judgement</hi> (I hope in ſome meaſure alſo to diſcern du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in difficult times and conditions) in ſenſe whereof, <hi>I deſired this liberty the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rſt day I was committed to this place,</hi> and many times ſince; and have often complained of it to God, and ſuch men as came near me, as a defect in the Government of this His Majeſties chiefeſt Priſon in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that care is not taken, nor liberty allowed, for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52790:6"/>
Chriſtian Priſoners to attend upon the publique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and preaching of the Word of God: I have in this reſpect often preferred the <hi>Compters,</hi> or <hi>Newgate</hi> (more baſe and deſpicable in vulgar account) before the Tower of <hi>London.</hi> It cannot I think be ſoberly (I am ſure not charitably) denied, that Chriſtian Priſoners, ought to have Chriſtian liberty and accommodation, in a Chriſtian Kingdom. It is ſuppoſed, a Priſoner bringeth with him into this place, ſome <hi>horrid crime, and notorious guilt,</hi> by reaſon whereof there is conceived but little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Priſon and death; therefore the hand of Juſtice which puniſheth the offence, ought in Chriſtian pity to ſeek the ſalvation of the ſoul, and (if poſſible) prevent the Malefactor from dying in, if he muſt dye for his ſin. I have often thought, that if the Heathen indulged <hi>Paul</hi> a liberty to <hi>Preach in Priſon,</hi> Chriſtians might and ought much more allow a <hi>Preacher</hi> liberty to <hi>hear</hi> the Word preached in Priſon. I hope it will be no offence to minde this Age, that amongſt other evils reflected (by ſuch as roſe up againſt him) on the Government of King <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt, his late Majeſtie of honorable memory, this was one,<note place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, p. 6.</note> and not the leaſt, <hi>Men were detained cloſe Priſoners, without the liberty of uſing Books, pen, ink, or paper, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them all the comforts of life, not permitting their wives to come to them; and for the compleating of that cruelty, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving them of the neceſſary means of Spiritual conſolation, not ſuffering them to go abroad, to enjoy Gods Ordinances in Gods Houſe, or Gods Miniſters to come to them, to adminiſter comfort to them in their Chambers.</hi> Let none therefore dare to cenſure this act as the reſult of a diſtreſſed condition, or baſe compliance by conſtraint of Priſon, againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſid.</hi> 2: Solemn pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip poſitive duty.</note>
                     <hi>Communion with the Church viſible, in all acts of ſolemn publique Worſhip, is an eſſential part of the Sanctification of the Sabbath, or Lords day, and poſitive, indiſpenſable duty of every particular ſoul called by the name of God;</hi> to be onely
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52790:6"/>
                     <hi>Superſeded</hi> by a real, inevitable neceſſity, with aſſurance to any, that <hi>God will have mercy, and not Sacrifice.</hi> This cannot be denyed by any, who obſerve God hath deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated the Sabbath an <hi>holy Convocation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Levit. 23.</note> Synagogues were on this ground erected and frequented, in all the Cities of <hi>Judah;</hi> that the Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 4 16. Acts 13 13, 14. &amp; 17.2.</note> 
                     <hi>fulfilling all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> and his Apoſtles <hi>in conſcience of duty,</hi> made it their cuſtom to go to the Synagogue every Sabbath day; that the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Aſcenſion of Chriſt,<note place="margin">John 20.19, 26. 1 Cor. 16.2.</note> held ſolemn Aſſemblies <hi>on the Lords day,</hi> the firſt day of the Week, and charged the Saints of their age, and in them all others, <hi>not to forſake the Aſſembling of themſelves together,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.25.</note> taxing the defect of ſome therein, <hi>as the manner of ſome is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As <hi>Solitary Sabbaths</hi> are in themſelves, ſo (God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) they have been, and are to me, the ſting of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned condition: I hope I can ſay, without vanity, as <hi>David</hi> in his exile,<note place="margin">Pſa 42.1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>As the Hart panteth for the water Brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee, O God: My ſoul thirſteth for the living God; When ſhall I come and appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? when I remember theſe things, I pour out my ſoul in me, for I have gone with the multitude: I went with them to the Houſe of God, with the voyce of joy and gladneſs, with the multitude that kept the holy day.</hi> I deny not God to be ſerved, and enjoyed in <hi>Solitary Worſhip,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.7.</note> but muſt needs obſerve, in <hi>Zion</hi> the Saints paſs <hi>from ſtrenth to ſtrength, every one appearing before God. Solemn publique Worſhip</hi> is Gods chief Ordinance, for the ſupport of his peoples faith; this is denominated, the <hi>Beauty of Gods Holineſs:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4. &amp; 96.9. and 110.3.</note> To this his preſence and power is promiſed, and in it chiefly predicated; attendance on this, is charged as his peoples duty, and diſcharged as their joy: The want of this is the <hi>Sacra fames,</hi> Spiritual famine,<note place="margin">Amos 8 11.</note> under want of which <hi>Davids</hi> faith was ready to faint, had it not been prevented by a ſpeedy and ſeaſonable ſupply: <hi>When I ſought to know this, it was too painful for me, until I went into the Sanctuary, then underſtood I their end,</hi> Pſal. 73.16, 17.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52790:7"/>
This therefore is not to be ſlighted, or neglected, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially deſired, or uſed; but moſt highly prized, earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly deſired, and joyfully imbraced, and not voluntarily declined on every light occaſion, and trivial exception, or friendly perſwaſion; but the grounds muſt be plain, clear, certain, and weighty, ſuch as I may with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence plead unto my God, as the apology of my abſence of choice, not conſtraint, in which I expect God ſhould <hi>have mercy on me,</hi> becauſe and for that he cannot have <hi>Sacrifice from me,</hi> which can be nothing but the <hi>reſtraining neceſſity</hi> of my condition, or my <hi>running into ſin</hi> to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs it.</p>
                  <p>My good Friend, you ſee my caſe is hard; and what now is my caſe, may ere long be yours, and others of Gods people: You yet enjoy a liberty of worſhipping God, in due and right order, and may drink the Waters of the Sanctuary in clean Veſſels; long may you enjoy it, and if God take pleaſure in me, he will in due time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore me to it; but if not, let him do what ſeemeth him good At the preſent I have no choice; if I will attend Gods <hi>publique Solemn Worſhip,</hi> I muſt do it in this place, and order, or not at all; whileſt I dread to give the leaſt occaſion of inſultation to the wicked, or offence to the weak, my conſcience is under the apprehenſion and aw of a poſitive indiſpenſible duty, which I dare not decline, unleſs on reaſons conſtituting a clear and unavoidable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: my preſent reſtraint doth indeed acquit me, and carry the guilt (of my abſence from Gods Houſe) from off me to others, I duly endeavouring, by all juſt means, to have the ſame removed; which once effected, what moral bar will lie upon my minde, and in my way, as a <hi>formal ſin,</hi> which I cannot without guilt break thorow? that is the queſtion I have deſired ſeriouſly to conſult, and by Scripture to reſolve: And on mature thoughts I muſt profeſs I finde not any, which will bear weight in the ballance of the Sanctuary, as that which I ſhall dare to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52790:7"/>
produce before the Lord, when demanded a reaſon of my voluntary abſence; on which he may not pronounce, <hi>He was bidden to the feaſt, but would not come, and therefore is not worthy, and hereafter ſhall not:</hi> For I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I never did, could, or yet can deny,<note place="margin">1. The Church of <hi>England</hi> a true Church and I a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> 
                     <hi>the being of the Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h of England</hi> (that is, the community of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in this Nation, incorporated by Baptiſm, profeſſing the true God and Jeſus Chriſt, and ſubjected to the Word and Sacraments, in the Miniſtery of Chriſts lawful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (for I never believed any <hi>National Priviledge,</hi> ſuch as was peculiar to the Jews, or the <hi>Hierarchical Order,</hi> and collective Conſtitution (which cannot be denied to be a meer humane and ſeparable adjunct, and is neither an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, nor regular Repreſentation) could or did give that appellation) nor diſown <hi>my own relation to it;</hi> and muſt therefore ſee ſome good ground for my non-communion with it, and for my choice of <hi>Solitary Worſhip of God,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then fellowſhip in its <hi>Solemn publique Worſhip,</hi> where and whileſt God affords his preſence, though with a grieved, ſtriving ſpirit, I dare not be abſent, though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I might avoid ſome burthen.</p>
                  <p>It is well known, I am not unacquainted with <hi>the Church renouncing, rending, ruining principles</hi> of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> and old ſeparating <hi>Browniſts,</hi> nor with the <hi>Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing practice</hi> of the (ſeemingly more ſober and ſerious) <hi>Independent,</hi> or Congregationaliſt; who ſometimes indeed pretend to own the <hi>being of this Church,</hi> but (by their Church-gathering, <hi>Self-Conſtitution,</hi> diſpencing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances by their <hi>ſelf-conſecration;</hi> profeſſed principle, that in <hi>England</hi> there is <hi>much matter for, but not the form of a Church,</hi> and ſo no Church at all, for <hi>forma dat eſſentiam;</hi> and with the height of confidence (to ſay no more of it) proclaiming themſelves <hi>the gathered Churches,</hi> contradiſtinct to the Nation, and all Chriſtians in it (as if they onely were the firſt fruits of <hi>Achaia,</hi> I mean <hi>England,</hi> an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52790:8"/>
Nation, who had never received the Goſpel, or Chriſt had not been preached among them, and profeſſed by them, nor any of her Inhabitants had been incorporated by Baptiſm, into Chriſts Catholique Body, but were to this day <hi>aliens and ſtrangers to the Houſhold of Faith, and Commonwealth of Iſrael</hi>) do plainly declare ſo to all rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal men (able and willing to diſcern) that the <hi>being of a Church in</hi> England is by them diſputed, yea, denied: But theſe I never did, nor could approve, and therefore I muſt preſume, none that ever knew me, and my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant conteſts, by preaching, writing, and ſuffering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and againſt them, can conceive this to be now any ſcruple to my conſcience, doubt to my ſoul, demur to my duty, or diverſion to my Communion with them, whoſe being a Church of Chriſt, I have ever, and openly aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and defended, and to whom I have ever profeſſed my own relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Prophane members deſtroy not the Church.</note>That theſe men urge, <hi>That many members in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>are rude and prophane in their Converſation, with their mouthes confeſſing, but in works denying God, and are not therefore fit matter for a Church,</hi> I do well know, and to my grief and ſhame do know to be true, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but to my comfort do know to be an Objection of no weight; for our queſtion is, concerning <hi>Communion</hi> with, not the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of a Church: That ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould not at firſt Conſtitution have been taken in, and having grown up, ought to have been cut off, and caſt out, I can and do yield, and conſent; but that the <hi>diſorder, defection and prophaneneſs of the members,</hi> or what is more, the <hi>Angels and Miniſters,</hi> hath reſolved the Church into a <hi>non-entity,</hi> and neceſſitated <hi>non-communion,</hi> (ſave in a new Conſtitution and Church gathering) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe, becauſe I finde nothing more plainer in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> then for a <hi>degenerate Vine,</hi> to retain the name and nature of a <hi>Vine,</hi> when it bringeth forth little ſave ſowre Grapes;<note place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note> nor is any thing more clearer in Scripture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52790:8"/>
then for the <hi>children of the Devil,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth 3 9. John 8.44.</note> to have <hi>Abrahaem to their father,</hi> and be the <hi>children of God, and Covenant of Graco,</hi> by viſible adminiſtration: or for <hi>diſorderly Chriſtians in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> to be called, and owned as <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Believers,</hi> a man covetous, a fornicator, and adulterer, an idolater,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.11. Rev. 3.1.</note> a drunkard, to be called a <hi>brother; Sardis</hi> having <hi>a name to live, but being dead,</hi> is declared one of the <hi>golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> among which Chriſt walketh; and when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to <hi>Titus,</hi> the Chriſtians in <hi>Crete</hi> were <hi>abominable, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> and to <hi>every good work reprobate,</hi> Titus 1, 13, 16. yet was <hi>Titus</hi> charged to <hi>rebuke them ſharply,</hi> not to diſown them, or decline communion with them, or to gather the <hi>fit matter,</hi> and <hi>orderly Chriſtians</hi> among them into a <hi>new Church form;</hi> nor are any among them adviſed, or direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo to do; a Ram, and a Goat cannot be denied to be of Chriſts flock on earth, though they may be turned on his left hand, at the day of judgment; Correction, and caſting out is the priviledge of a Church member; and ſuppoſeth its capacity in their object, though an <hi>inceſtuous perſon:</hi> the prophaneneſſe of the members of this Church may and muſt provoke my <hi>brotherly admonition,</hi> miniſterial reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the <hi>Churches Cenſures</hi> againſt them, but will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver warrant my <hi>non-communion with them,</hi> or voluntary ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from Gods ſolemn publick worſhip celebrated among them; becauſe it doth not <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> by any due <hi>order,</hi> or <hi>divine direction;</hi> diſcharge their relation to Chriſts Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick viſible body, ſo long as God knoweth them as his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> (though deſerving) having not received from him a Bill of Divorce; I may be burdened to ſee their lewdneſſe and lightneſſe, but muſt not forſake the Bride-chamber, nor his worſhip therein celebrated: without all doubt, the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of thoſe <hi>within the Church</hi> (though <hi>diſorderly,</hi> and as ſuch to be judged) is vaſtly different from Turks, Jews, and Pagans, and thoſe <hi>without the Church;</hi> who refuſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the true God, and Chriſt, or obedience to them; the one being ſubjected to Gods <hi>special pastoral, paternal care;</hi> in the caſe of their very diſorder and aberrations; whileſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52790:9"/>
the other only enjoy Gods <hi>common providence</hi> as do other creatures, the works of his hands.</p>
                  <p>What hath been urged to nullifie this Church from (what this kind of men will needs ſuppoſe to be) the form there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">Parochial di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and good.</note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> that they are by <hi>Parochial conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt never ordained Pariſhes,</hi> hath been often, and abundantly anſwered, by many, and among others, I have already ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken to it in my <hi>Bethſhemiſh clouded,</hi> and ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now only ſay, <hi>Parochial diſtribution</hi> is no <hi>constitution,</hi> nor any <hi>eſſential form of the Church;</hi> ſo as that bare ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple habitation within ſuch bounds, ſhould <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> without further capacity, or qualification make men <hi>Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;</hi> or their removal, or non-reſidence within this or that Pariſh, (as do Merchants and Mariners) ſhould diſcharge their relation to the Church: but it is a <hi>Political order,</hi> and <hi>convenient diſtribution of the Church Catholick viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> to <hi>particular Aſsemblies;</hi> for the due and more eaſie Celebration of Gods publick worſhip; the Lord Jeſus foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Church Catholick, and univerſal, into which Baptiſm is the Ordinance of Catholick inciſion, and imitation; and excommunication is the Ordinance of Catholick exciſion, and diſcharge; but nature, and the neceſſity of order doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it into particular Aſſemblies, according to humane di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion: and no order can more conveniently circumſcribe particular ſocieties of the Church, than <hi>vicinity,</hi> and <hi>cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> This the holy Ghoſt doth plainly digitate, by deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating the firſt plants of Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">Rome, Corinth, Galatia, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>and the like.</hi>
                     </note> by the <hi>places</hi> where they were planted, not by the firſt <hi>planters,</hi> or <hi>after Paſtors:</hi> blaming it as a <hi>Schiſm in the Church,</hi> to ſay, <hi>I am of Paul, I of Apollo,</hi> and <hi>I of Cephas;</hi> and indeed this diſtribution doth much facilitate the inſpection of the Paſtor, or brethren, beyond what the <hi>Covenant conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of Congregationaliſts is capable of; whereby ſome living in <hi>York</hi> are members of a Church in <hi>London.</hi> Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Diviſion then being the benefit of the Church, and members thereof in Chriſtian Cities, Countries, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is ſo far from blame and avoidance, that it is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52790:9"/>
and approved by men of prudence, and order, and can never neceſſitate, or warrant any mans non-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Chriſtian Aſſemblies thus diſtributed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently aſſembled.</p>
                  <p>Unto ſuch as ſtumble themſelves, and would have others ſo to do, at Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not know that it was <hi>rightly gathered,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Englands</hi> Church was rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted at the firſt.</note> 
                     <hi>and conſtituted at the firſt;</hi> I ſhall briefly ſay, Hiſtory, (the beſt evidence of an ancient Act,) doth aſſure us that the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel was firſt preached,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity was firſt planted in our Iſlands by the Apoſtles, or Apoſtolical men,</hi> which (no doubt) did with all care, rightly lay here the right foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Gods Church, and if we may (as in caſes of this nature, we muſt) judge (a poſterior) the <hi>certainty of the root,</hi> by the extent, and quality of the branches; the <hi>foundation</hi> by the Dimenſions and duration of the Fabrick; can any man reading the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Stories of the eminent Martyrs of Chriſtianity found in this Church, in all ages, ſince the times of the Apoſtles unto this day, and not conclude the Church was at firſt rightly planted, and founded? theſe men ſhall do well to reſolve the old queſtion ever put by the Non-conformiſts to the Browniſts (theſe mens progenitors) if they be begotten to God, in what Church, and by what Ordinances were they converted? was it not the Church of <hi>England?</hi> we (whom they to ſerve their deſigne, will own as Saints, and declare fit matter for a Church.) muſt profeſſe our ſelves ſprouts from this plant; their Charity is not ſure ſo irrational, as to believe men may gather <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pes of Thorns,</hi> or <hi>Figgs of Thiſtles,</hi> for if ſo, their gathering Churches will be found needleſſe, whileſt Saints grow in <hi>Infidel ſoils,</hi> and Gods houſe exiſteth without the laying any <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe men ſhall do well to conſider,<note place="margin">Knowledge of a Church it firſt conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note> whether the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the mode and order of firſt planting and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Church, be neceſſary to every member related to it. In <hi>England</hi> we finde ſocieties profeſſing the true God, and Chriſt; baptized into his name, worſhipping him
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52790:10"/>
by his own Ordinances; this is the <hi>forme of a Church;</hi> and doth ſuppoſe and imply a <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Foundation,</hi> by which it is animated and preſerved; But muſt we needs know how it was at the firſt laid, or planted? though by length of time it is worn out of ſight, and over-grown with earth and weeds? are we bound to renounce the <hi>Vine,</hi> and run out of the <hi>houſe,</hi> unleſſe we pluck up the <hi>root,</hi> and raze the foundation to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſelves herein? if ſo, God help the illiterate ſouls, and weak capacities not capable to conceive, or well underſtand the ſame; is Chriſts Church planted for an age only? that every ſucceeding generation muſt tranſplant? gathering of Churches did indeed begin the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles;</hi> muſt it needs be continued to the end of the <hi>Revelation?</hi> to the coming of the Lord to judgment? I finde not <hi>Paul</hi> in his <hi>joyning himſelf</hi> to the Church, nor <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila</hi> in their travels, and communion with different Churches, make any demurre on this enquiry; and I dare not think the holy Ghoſt would have concealed from us a point of ſo great importance.</p>
                  <p>My good friend; upon the whole of this Objection, I muſt let you know that my ſerious and deliberate thoughts do diſſent from the Concluſions concerning the <hi>matter and form of a Church,</hi> ſtated by the <hi>ſelf-conſecrated Officers of the hundred and twenty ſelf-conſtituted gathered Churches,</hi> which of late years met at the <hi>Savoy:</hi> but aſſent unto the determination of Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his advice to the brethren of old <hi>England</hi> at the cloſe of his way of the Churches in <hi>New-England,</hi> (viz.) <hi>The work is not to make them Churches, which were none before; (for the Gospel having been prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in</hi> England <hi>by Apoſtles, or Apoſtolical men, they were without doubt rightly planted) but to reduce them to the Primitive purity they had in their firſt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And (here my friend,) I muſt deſire the Independents will not be offended, that I propoſe them as the preſent prime promoters of the <hi>nonentity of the Church of England,</hi> by way of barre to <hi>Communion with her,</hi> and a principle of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52790:10"/>
                     <hi>ſeparation from her:</hi> for that (notwithſtanding their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary profeſſions of what they cannot ſoberly, charitably, and rationally deny) their common ſuggeſtion in <hi>England,</hi> is <hi>fit matter, but not the form,</hi> (which is the eſſe) of the Church; their <hi>Savoy concluſions,</hi> and paganizing <hi>Church-gathering practice,</hi> do loudly proclaim them the off-ſpring of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and poſterity of the rigid <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> ever withſtood by the ſober, and ſerious Non-Conformiſts, ſince <hi>Englands</hi> Reformation: and in this point the <hi>ſummum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> of thoſe ſeveral, ſpecifical, ſelf-conſtituted Sects, which have confounded our Church; the odium of whoſe Schiſm from it, defended by Rebellion, Schiſm, and horrid Treaſon is at this day moſt ſadly (though falſly) reflected on the moſt loyal, ſober, ſerious, reforming, non-conforming Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; to the weakning their hands, and retarding, yea di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting their progreſſe in an humble, argumentative, and patient purſuit of Chriſts Ordinances, and due authority of Chriſts Officers, to be reſtored, and exerciſed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> by me ever owned, and now lamented, but not to be deſerted.</p>
                  <p>Such as fancie the Church of <hi>England</hi> was <hi>loſt in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Popery and Antichriſtianiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Englands</hi> Church loſt not its being in Popery.</note> may by their own obſervation correct the ſame; and be conſtrained to confeſſe, there is in this reſpect no more cauſe of ſtumble as to the <hi>entity of this Church,</hi> then was as to the <hi>being of the Jews,</hi> when overſpread with Idolatry, in their many defections from God; for in <hi>Englands</hi> worſt times they may finde a perſecuted <hi>Elias,</hi> a <hi>John Wickliffe,</hi> with many other moſt eminent branches, bringing forth the Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Goſpel Grapes, to the bleeding out their very lives, beſides <hi>Obadiah's fifties</hi> hidden in Caves, by the violence of perſecution; certainly the <hi>Root muſt abide,</hi> or how, or whence could theſe branches ſpring? Yea, the winter ſtorms of Popery paſſing away, and the floods of Antichriſtianiſm aſſwaging, though not dryed up, and the chief weeds of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition being plucked up, though ſome remain; how hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52790:11"/>
this Church revived, flouriſhed, and ſent out many moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and pious branches, without any new plantation? Yea, conveyed unto themſelves (who queſtion her being) the <hi>truth of Grace,</hi> and Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, if ever they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it? I bleſſe God I have learned to diſcern between the <hi>ſubject,</hi> and its <hi>ſeparable adjuncts</hi> though never ſo vile, and do believe the <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>Chriſts Church,</hi> though vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated and defiled with <hi>Idolatrous administrations;</hi> all, nor indeed any defection is an actual divorce; if <hi>adulterous Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jet. 3.</note> on a ſummons to repentance, do return, and put away her abominations, ſhe loſeth not her relation to God; nor doth the high places continued under his reformation, make God or his people to forſake her; the <hi>Temple of God</hi> abides his, when given to be trodden under the feet of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: yea, when the Antichriſt the man of ſin, ſitteth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; this notion may poſſibly ſound better to ſome eares from <hi>New-England,</hi> than from the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> let it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be thence receiv'd; <hi>If Antichriſt muſt ſit in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and the Courts of the Temple be given to the Antichriſtiaen Gentiles for a certain time to tread under foot, then there was a true Church ſtate where he ſate, and whileſt he ſate there, and it was the true meaſured Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe Courts he did tread under fo t, nor can there be Antichriſt, unleſſe there be the Temple of God and Courts thereof, where he is; and if ever Antichrist ſate in</hi> England, <hi>then there was the Temple of God there; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſate in it, and whileſt he ſate in it, as was alſo in other reformed Churches, the Temple or Church is the ſubject wherein he muſt ſit; the Antichriſtian ſeat is not the ſubject, nor conſtituteth it, but is an accident vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſubject, and ſeparable from it; the removing therefore of Antichriſtianity, doth not deſtroy the ſubject, or make it ceaſe to be; but changeth it into the better ſtate, in which it was before thus accidentally vitiated:</hi> this is the aſſertion of Mr. <hi>Phillips</hi> of <hi>Water-town</hi> in <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England was Chriſts Church</hi> before the <hi>Antichriſtian
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52790:11"/>
deluge,</hi> under the power of Popery; and ſince it was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out, and ſo ſhe at this day (notwithſtanding her back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding) doth abide; God provoked hath not yet removed his Candleſtick, or given her a bill of divorce, as he juſtly may, and I fear yet will, if I then deny Communion with ſuch of her aſſemblies, I have a liberty to attend and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and make my appeal to God on the account of her <hi>non-entity;</hi> with a Lord ſhe was not, or I know her not to be the Church and Spouſe, my heart would condemn me in the guilt of a <hi>notorious lye, groundleſſe, and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cenſure,</hi> and ſo make my <hi>wilful ſolitary devotion,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſad, becauſe exceeding ſinful.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I hitherto could not, nor yet can,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Englands</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient bar to Communion.</note> conceive the corruptions of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a ſufficient ground, or warrantable barre to my <hi>non-Communion</hi> with her ſolemn aſſemblies in her publick worſhip.</p>
                  <p>I do not ſay that <hi>Separation in all Caſes is unlawful,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Separation from the world and <hi>Babylon</hi> allowed.</note> I well know Chriſtians are <hi>called out of,</hi> and <hi>ſeparated from the world,</hi> in their firſt acceſſion to the Church of Chriſt; but this is not our Caſe, who (do as is before noted) own the Church of <hi>England</hi> as reſolved into that capacity: I know alſo <hi>ſeparation from Babylon</hi> the ſeat of Antichriſt is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, directed and charged by the Lord, on all his people; and unto this alſo the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth profeſſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Englands</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld with <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> and others,</note> and cannot be denied to have attained, and therefore ſtands diſtinct from the one, under the Epithite <hi>(Reformed)</hi> as well as from the other by the Appellation <hi>(Church):</hi> ſo as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at I dare not deeme <hi>England</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> (thoſe objects of a ſerious, ſacred ſeparation, and non-communion) to both which ſhe is found contradiſtinct.</p>
                  <p>That there are in the Church of <hi>England</hi> (eſpecially in her preſent relapſed eſtate) <hi>many and groſſe corruptions, grievous to the Spirit of God and his people,</hi> calling for the zealous admonitions, and moſt faithful rebukes of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; is alas! too too legible, and apparent, to be denied by any; yet, (when I conſult the Scriptures) I cannot but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52790:12"/>
finde as great (yea if poſſible) greater corruptions in thoſe whom God, and his people owned as his <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Spouſe;</hi> and yet <hi>ſeparation,</hi> or <hi>voluntary non-communion,</hi> was never practiſed, adviſed, or indulged, but the contrary thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Will any object unto us the <hi>prophaneneſſe of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prophaneneſſe of Miniſters &amp; miniſtration.</note> 
                     <hi>rudeneſse and diſorder of the miniſtration of Gods worſhip,</hi> we yeild it is too viſibly true; but more vile admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators, or irregular adminiſtrations cannot be, than were the <hi>ſons of Eli</hi> in their ſervice; who made the people to <hi>loath the offerings of the Lord,</hi> and were rebuked, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Samuel,</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Now the ſons of Eli were ſons of Belial, they knew not the Lord, and the Prieſts cuſtome with the people was this, when any man offered Sacrifice, the Prieſts ſervant came while the fleſh was in ſeething, with a fleſh-hook in his hand, and he ſtruck it into the pan, or kettle, or Caldron, or pot; all that the fleſh-hook brought up, the Prieſt took for himſelf, ſo they did in Shilo unto all the Iſraelites that came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, alſo before they burned the far, the Prieſts ſervant came and ſaid to the man that ſacrificed, give me fleſh for to roſt for the Prieſt, for he will not have ſodden fleſh of thee, but raw; and if any man ſaid unto them, let them not faile to burn the fat preſently, and then take as much as thy ſoul deſireth, then he would anſwer him, nay, but thou ſhalt give it me now, and if not, I will take it by force wherefore</hi> (by this horrid diſorder defended by violence) <hi>the ſin of the young men was very great before the Lord, for men abhorred the offering of the Lord,</hi> and in <hi>verſe</hi> 22. it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that <hi>Eli's</hi> ſons <hi>lay with the women that aſſembled at the door of the Tabernacle of the Congregation:</hi> O horrid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, moſt heaven-daring villany! yet I find not that any God-fearing-Iſraelite <hi>forſook the Sanctuary,</hi> or durſt <hi>forbear their Sacrifice;</hi> nor did <hi>Samuel</hi> (who reproved, and denounced Gods judgment againſt this prophaneneſſe) ever adviſe, or direct the ſame: the Scribes and Phariſees in the dayes of our Saviour, <hi>ſaid, but did not; laid heavie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52790:12"/>
on the people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>which themſelves would not touch with one of their fingers; they under pretence of long prayers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured widows houſes, they would neither enter into heaven themſelves, nor ſuffer ſuch as would;</hi> yet the <hi>Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> who reproved them, <hi>heard them,</hi> and charged his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to <hi>hear them, becauſe they ſate in Moſes ſeat;</hi> Let it be obſerved and remembred, the <hi>Authority</hi> may, but the <hi>quality</hi> of the Miniſter doth not adde to, or abſtract from the entity, or efficacy of Gods Ordinances,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27.</note> he may preach to my ſalvation, who is himſelf a caſtaway.</p>
                  <p>Do any object the <hi>preaching falſe doctrine;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Corruption in Doctrine and Worſhip.</note> 
                     <hi>publick reading the Apocripha</hi> as part of Gods Word; <hi>innovations in worſhip, polluting Gods Ordinances,</hi> or <hi>injuſtice in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline;</hi> I ſhall neither deny, nor excuſe the ſame: only ſay as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to the Church in his dayes, <hi>there were falſe Prophets among the people, even as there are falſe Teachers among you;</hi> the true Prophets of God in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> were ordinarily confronted by the falſe; there wanted not an <hi>Hannaniah,</hi> to break the Yokes of <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> nor a proud <hi>Paſhur</hi> to put him in the Stocks, in the Gate of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin,</hi> when he <hi>only declared Gods mind, warned of Gods approaching judgments,</hi> and withſtood the <hi>perjurious breach of the Oath of God,</hi> which was upon the <hi>King, and Kingdom;</hi> nor is any thing more plain, than <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſetting their <hi>poſts, by Gods poſts;</hi> their <hi>Altars by Gods Altars;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 8.6.43.8.</note> ſetting up in Gods houſe the very <hi>Image of Jealouſie,</hi> inſomuch that Gods Prophets were ordinarily <hi>invective;</hi> and <hi>vehemently reproving</hi> in their Miniſtery; and indeed extraordinarily raiſed up to that very end! yet we find (not in all their Cals to Repentance) one <hi>Caution</hi> againſt <hi>Communion with the Church,</hi> or <hi>Call unto ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>paration:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mark 8.15.7.3.</note> In the dayes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo corrupt in their doctrine, that he Cautioned his Diſciples to <hi>beware of the leaven of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> they <hi>made the Word of God of none effect, by their traditions of the Elders;</hi> they enervated the Law by moſt ſtrait and falſe interpretations thereof; In <hi>worſhip</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novated, and with great ſeverity impoſed, their own <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52790:13"/>
Phariſaical <hi>Rites,</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions:</hi> they propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Temple,</hi> and made Gods houſe a <hi>Den of Thieves;</hi> and in their Diſcipline they made acts of <hi>Neceſſity, Charity</hi> and <hi>piety,</hi> cenſurable unto a <hi>caſting out of the Synagogues;</hi> againſt all which the whole Miniſtery of the Lord Jeſus was <hi>highly invective,</hi> and <hi>ſeverely rebuking,</hi> yet he neither <hi>diſowned</hi> them as a <hi>Church, denyed communion with them,</hi> all his time on earth; or <hi>directed</hi> any of his <hi>Diſciples ſo to do,</hi> ſo long as God continued his preſence and Ordinances to and among them: but on the contrary pleaded for them (as the very fountain of Salvation) in oppoſition to the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, You worſhip you know not what, but we know what we worſhip, for ſalvation is of the Jews:</hi> he ſent his clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lepers to ſhew themſelves to the Prieſts,<note place="margin">John 4.22.</note> and offer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> confined his Miniſtry and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to them, till after the vaile of the Temple was rent, in token of the expiration of their worſhip and departure of God; accounting them children, and all others dogs; and charged the Diſciples to hear them who ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat; under all their God-provoking Church annihilating corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he neither practiſed or preſcribed a <hi>non-communion</hi> or <hi>ſeparation;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 John 2.6.</note> And in all extreams, I deſire to make him my pattern, and <hi>walk as he walked,</hi> who never went aſtray.</p>
                  <p>Do any ſtumble at the <hi>prophaneneſſe of the members,</hi> and the <hi>neglect of corrective diſcipline, rudeneſſe and irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the uſe of Gods Ordinances,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prophadeſs of members, and diſorder in Miniſtration.</note> 
                     <hi>confuſed method,</hi> and the <hi>diſorder of popular acclamations in publick prayer, and other acts of worſhip;</hi> I wiſh I could ſay theſe ſtones lay not in their way, or that they were in my power to remove them; but I think they run on a much greater Rock, who <hi>run out of Gods Church,</hi> or <hi>from ſolemn publick worſhip</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereof: for the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> was greatly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and provoked the ſeverity of Apoſtolical reprehenſion; and that once and again;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.1, 2.10.21.11.20.21.14.26. 2 Cos. 12.20, 21</note> there being amongſt them <hi>inceſt not to be named among the Gentiles,</hi> and an <hi>heaven-daring oſtentation in it,</hi> inſtead of correction of it; a <hi>participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the table of Divels,</hi> by their attendance on the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52790:13"/>
Idol-feaſts of the Infidels; a <hi>rude and deboist drunken Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at the Lords Supper,</hi> intermingled and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Love-feaſts: <hi>intollerable diſorder in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſsemblie,</hi> all ſpeaking <hi>at one and the ſame moment, their very women not keeping ſilence;</hi> and that in <hi>different matters</hi> and <hi>tongues,</hi> every one had <hi>his Pſalm, his Prayer, his Revelation, his Propheſie, his gift of Tongues,</hi> (in all which reſpects they were more confuſed than our popular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations) and conſtrained the Apoſtles to check them, by the nature of God, as a <hi>God of order, and not of confuſion;</hi> in all theſe the Apoſtle adviſed, and endeavoured with all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority a <hi>Reformation,</hi> but not <hi>ſeparation,</hi> or <hi>non-communion,</hi> nor <hi>tranſplantation</hi> into a new gathered Church; I cannot imagine he would make <hi>Schiſm from the Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.4.</note> a ſigne of a <hi>spiritual,</hi> who judged <hi>Schiſm in the Church an evidence of a carnal mind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Do men complain (as they have cauſe) that ſome <hi>Roman Rites, and order was retained,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> Rites.</note> 
                     <hi>when this Church was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed;</hi> let them conſider many pious Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> have their reforming governments ſtained with a <hi>but the high places were not taken away,</hi> but <hi>the people went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to worſhip:</hi> yet I finde not that any God-fearing Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, who loathed thoſe Reliques of Idolatry, ever barred themſelves becauſe thereof, from Gods Altar and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>My very ſoul is grieved to conſider <hi>Englands back-ſliding,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Backſliding &amp; Lukewarmneſs</note> 
                     <hi>Indulgence of erronious Doctors and doctrines, formality and lukewarmneſse in Religion;</hi> yet when I obſerve that <hi>Epheſus</hi> who <hi>loſt her firſt love, Pergamus</hi> indulging the <hi>doctrine of Balaam,</hi> and the <hi>Nicolaitans, Thyatira</hi> ſuffering the <hi>woman Jezabel, who called her ſelf a propheteſse to teach, and to deceive Gods people; Sardis</hi> having <hi>a name to live, but being dead,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea, Englands</hi> Counterpart, ſo <hi>lukewarm that no good is ſpoken of her;</hi> by all which theſe <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches were ruſted, and therefore reproved by the Lord, yet not rejected; but repreſented to the world as the <hi>Starres</hi> he held in his right hand, and <hi>golden Candleſticks</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52790:14"/>
among which he walked; I dare not diſown her <hi>relation to God;</hi> diſclaim <hi>mine own relation to her,</hi> nor voluntarily decline <hi>communion with her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Corruptions are not all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note>My good friend, <hi>all corruptions</hi> in Gods Church and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, are <hi>diſpleaſing to God, and diſtaſtful to his people</hi> imbracing the ſimplicity of the Goſpel; but <hi>all corruptions</hi> are not alike in <hi>operation, quality, and extent,</hi> nor of a like <hi>influence on Gods Church and worſhip:</hi> conſider therefore ſome corruptions are <hi>ſubſtantial, and intrinſecal,</hi> vitiating the <hi>very ſubject,</hi> and ſo <hi>univerſally spread through the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, that it cannot be uſed without ſin;</hi> others are <hi>circumſtantial and extrinſecal</hi> to the ſame, <hi>vain, needleſſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants,</hi> ſuperadded by mans will, but which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Gods Ordinances remain entire, and <hi>exactly his,</hi> and may be uſed without participation in the affixed corruption.</p>
                  <p>Some corruptions incident to Gods Church and worſhip, I ſay are <hi>ſubſtantial and intrinſecal,</hi> (not ariſing out of Gods Ordinance as the genuine product, and effect thereof, but) <hi>entring into the very body of the Church</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance of Gods worſhip,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Corruptions ſubſtantial and intrinſecal.</note> as a Spider into wine, or venemous Worme into an Apple; ſo as to <hi>vitiate the ſubject,</hi> (that it cannot be uſed with ſafety) and <hi>nulliſie the very Ordinances of God,</hi> that it <hi>altereth their very nature</hi> to the loſſe of their effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and tranſmit <hi>certain deſtruction</hi> to ſuch as ſit under the ſame; yea, which is done either by changing the <hi>matter,</hi> and retaining the <hi>eſsential conſtitutive form,</hi> as by a ſolemne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>cutting off a Dogs head,</hi> or <hi>offering ſwines blood,</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Lamb,</hi> or a <hi>Kid;</hi> a <hi>baptizing</hi> (as ſome have done) by <hi>fire</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtead of <hi>water:</hi> or retaining the <hi>matter,</hi> but changing the <hi>eſſential forme,</hi> as did <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> worſhipping the <hi>true God,</hi> by the <hi>very Sacrifices,</hi> and in the <hi>very order</hi> himſelf appointed; but before <hi>ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed Symbols, Calves</hi> to the one, and the <hi>Dove</hi> to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a <hi>ſelf-appointed place, Dan and Berſheba</hi> to the one, <hi>Mount Gerizim</hi> to the other; and by <hi>ſelf-conſecrated Prieſts,</hi> the loweſt of the people, <hi>and ſo departing from the Temple in Jeruſalem,</hi> Gods <hi>Ark in it,</hi> and the <hi>Tribe of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52790:14"/>
Levi:</hi> all which were eſſentiall to the form of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and thus did the <hi>Corinthians</hi> eating and drinking at the Idol Sacrifices, which the Apoſtle ſeverely corrected, with a <hi>(ye cannot par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ake of the Table of the Lord, and the table of Devils, ye cannot drink of the Cup of the Lord, and the cup of Devils;)</hi> and by pointing them unto the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential form of the Sacrament, <hi>the Cup of bleſſing, which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt?</hi> and <hi>the Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> Of this nature is Baptiſm,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note> by a <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife,</hi> or any other private hand, though with <hi>water,</hi> and <hi>in the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt;</hi> or by water and a lawful Miniſter, but in the name of <hi>God the Father of all things, and Truth the Mother of all things;</hi> as I have read ſome have done.</p>
                  <p>Corruptions <hi>extrinſecal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Corruptions extrinſecal and circumſtantial.</note> 
                     <hi>and c'rcumſtantial</hi> are Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <hi>ſuperadded unto,</hi> and ſo <hi>concomitant with,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about Gods Ordinances;</hi> but <hi>enter not into,</hi> nor do <hi>vitiate their ſubject:</hi> the which (theſe notwithſtanding) doth exiſt in <hi>matter,</hi> and <hi>eſſential form,</hi> perfect and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire; capable of due operation, in their own courſe and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as ſtinking fiſh doth nouriſh; or water pudled, or in an unclean veſſel, doth quench the thirſt; and theſe are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome matter <hi>ſuperadded,</hi> (not intermingled with, or deſtructive to Gods Ordinances, ſuch as were the <hi>high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, poſts by Gods posts, threſholds by his threſholds, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar by his Altar</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto the very <hi>Image of Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> ſet up in Gods houſe, which yet remained his, and as ſuch was continued, preſerved and acknowledged. The Lord Jeſus found the Temple his <hi>Fathers houſe of Prayer,</hi> though made a <hi>Den of theeves;</hi> and ſuch is our <hi>Croſſe in Baptiſm,</hi> though ſeemingly ſacramental, yet diſtinct from Gods imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seal of the Covenant; and ſuch is a <hi>Roman linnen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture</hi> in miniſtration of Gods worſhip by a lawfull Miniſter; or ſome <hi>corrupt, rude and unſutable miniſterial method and order,</hi> (which is the veſſel, and only inſtrument of convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance though unclean) <hi>of adminiſtration:</hi> ſuch was the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52790:15"/>
and unfitting ſnatching of the Prieſts part of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, by the ſons of</hi> Eli, <hi>the confuſed acclamations</hi> of the Church of <hi>Corinth, ſpeaking all at once,</hi> different <hi>matters,</hi> in <hi>different tongues;</hi> and our <hi>impoſed method, diſorderly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> of publick Prayer, by <hi>Verſicles, Reſponds, abrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> abreviations and <hi>popular acclamations,</hi> with artificial ſinging by boyes, and baſe fellows thereunto appointed: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all which Gods Ordinances abide a <hi>ſubject compleat, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>formerly exiſtent, and distinct from theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added corruptions; operative unto ſalvation;</hi> and therefore may not be declined, or diſowned.</p>
                  <p>Corruptions <hi>intrinſecal,</hi> are indeed ſuch as do not only warrant, but <hi>neceſſitate non-communion,</hi> yea <hi>ſeparation of the higheſt nature,</hi> as a duty indiſpenſable: In ſence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all thoſe in <hi>Iſrael who feared God, and ſet their hearts to ſeek the Lord, prayed for,</hi> and (according to divine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections) <hi>departed from Dan, and Berſheba,</hi> forſook the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſſemblies <hi>Jeroboam had conſtituted,</hi> and followed the <hi>Tribe of Levi,</hi> Gods only Miniſters, unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Gods only place of publick ſolemn worſhip; and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour reſolved the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> her enquiry concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place of worſhip, with a (<hi>ye know not what ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; for ſalvation is of the Jews:</hi> This is the very ground of the Reformed Churches <hi>departure,</hi> and <hi>non-communion</hi> with <hi>Rome;</hi> who though ſhe be (by original conſtitution) the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> is become the very <hi>ſeat of Antichriſt;</hi> and by the ſame ſo <hi>vitiated</hi> that her Miniſtrations are the <hi>cup of abomination by which ſhe hath made the Nations drunk,</hi> having (by her <hi>interceſſions of, and to Saints,</hi> the <hi>Popes infallibility, divine power and properties, and by her expiatory Sacrifices</hi>) diſowned, and nullified (as much as in her lieth) Chriſts mediatory offices: and (by <hi>dividing the elements, deſtroying the outward ſigne, eſſential to a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and on a fancied <hi>tranſubſtanciation,</hi> turning it into a <hi>Sacrifice for quick and dead</hi>) nullified Chriſts Ordinances: and (by many other intrinſecal evils) poyſoned Gods whole worſhip, and rendred it directly <hi>deſtructive to ſalvation;</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52790:15"/>
is therefore preſented to us under the Appellation <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the very abſtract; <hi>ſpiritual Sodom, and Egypt;</hi> and ſo the object of our <hi>departure,</hi> adviſed, with (a <hi>leſt ye partake of her ſins:</hi> which were and are ſo univerſally diffuſed, and hath ſo farre vitiated the ſubject, that a guilt will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by meer Communion.</p>
                  <p>Corruptions extrinſecal may,<note place="margin">Extrinſecal corruptions warrant no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</note> and muſt <hi>grieve the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Gods people;</hi> occaſion their <hi>loud complaints,</hi> his Miniſters moſt <hi>zealous reproofs,</hi> and the <hi>ſtud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of all, to prevent and remove them;</hi> becauſe <hi>ſcandals to the Church, prejudicial</hi> (though not directly deſtructive, <hi>to ſalvation) diſhonourable to Religion, and the God</hi> (whoſe prerogative it is to preſcribe every pin, and the very ſnuffers to be uſed in his Houſe,<note place="margin">1 King 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>) and is therefore <hi>highly displeaſing to God;</hi> provoking him to <hi>rend a Kingdom from the houſe of David,</hi> to <hi>loath,</hi> and at leaſt to <hi>leave</hi> his <hi>holy place,</hi> and <hi>remove his Candlestick</hi> from ſuch as will not fear him in the <hi>ſimplicity of his own institutions;</hi> without the vain and needleſſe Appendants of their own inventions: But yet theſe cannot warrant <hi>ſeparation</hi> or <hi>voluntary non-communion,</hi> becauſe the Church abideth related to God as <hi>his Spouſe;</hi> his worſhip and Ordinances remain for matter and eſſential form <hi>entire,</hi> and <hi>exactly his own;</hi> notwithſtanding the concomitancy of ſome ſuper-added matter; or the unfit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial method, and order by which they are diſpenſed; and Gods preſence is to them <hi>continued,</hi> (though with a grieved, ſtriving ſpirit, threatning his departure) and thereby we are <hi>under a poſſibility of ſalvation;</hi> (though engaged to more care and induſtry) this was the caſe of the Prophets, our Saviour and his Diſciples, the Church of the Jews, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, under the many parallel (yea tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ours,) corruptions, before mentioned, without any preſcript, or practice, of Separation, or Non-Communion.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtian Friend, it is too evident, That <hi>many and great Corruptions are</hi> to our ſin, and ſhame <hi>retained;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Caſe of <hi>England</hi> under corruption.</note> and to the aggravation thereof (with an high hand, and defiance of the God of Jealouſie) <hi>returned</hi> (after a Solemn and Sacred
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52790:16"/>
Expulſion) <hi>into our Church;</hi> but yet they are <hi>extrinſecal,</hi> and not of the <hi>ſubſtance of Gods Worſhip,</hi> which for Matter, and eſſential Form, remaineth <hi>entire, and properly his own:</hi> (though not ſo acceptable) <hi>under, as well as without them;</hi> and will not therefore warrant my Separation, or Non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſo far as to lie at Home, or loyter in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, until the Common-Prayer (whereby God is <hi>truly,</hi> though not <hi>orderly,</hi> invocated, and worſhipped; wherein I (as a Member of that Church) <hi>am interested,</hi> and unto which, as it is <hi>Publick Solemn Prayer</hi> (though in an unſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Method) my <hi>Amen</hi> is an indiſpenſable Duty) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Administrations</hi> of Gods Worſhip among us, are indeed <hi>nauſeous,</hi> and <hi>unhealthful,</hi> but not <hi>void,</hi> or <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous;</hi> our waters are <hi>bitter, and pudled,</hi> but not <hi>poyſonous;</hi> our Paſtures are <hi>trodden down,</hi> and the proud <hi>of the Flock do puſh us with Horn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
                     <hi>and with Hoof;</hi> but we are not yet driven out of <hi>Christs Fold,</hi> not dare not we ſay our <hi>Paſture is quite taken from us:</hi> To be plain, Under all our Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, we muſt not, we cannot, we dare not deny the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>eſsential Form of Gods Ordinances and Worſhip, is continued to us;</hi> though ſome ſuperſtitious Rites are unto them annexed, which are apparent Appendants, redundant to, and ſeparable from, and not <hi>vitiating,</hi> deſtructive, or anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilating to their Subject; and are therefore pretended and profeſſed (by the Canons appropriated to this Church) to be <hi>Acts of Order and Ornament,</hi> rather than of <hi>Worſhip, and Adoration to God;</hi> and they are ſuch wherein the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are generally <hi>paſſive,</hi> not <hi>active.</hi> Baptiſm is <hi>fully and formally Gods Ordinance,</hi> though the <hi>Croſs</hi> be needleſly, and ſuperſtitiouſly added thereunto; and the <hi>Parent</hi> (by virtue of whoſe intereſt in Gods Covenant, the Child receiveth the Seal) is unjuſtly excluded; and a deputation of <hi>Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Godmothers,</hi> is groundleſly impoſed: <hi>The Word of God is not excluded,</hi> though now and then, a piece of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripha</hi> is unwarrantably read in the publick Aſſembly; nor doth it ceaſe to be the Word of God, becauſe it is <hi>unfitly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52790:16"/>
mangled</hi> into parts and parcels, <hi>urduly fixed</hi> unto <hi>places, unreaſonably appropriated</hi> unto <hi>dayes and times,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Surplices and canting quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſinging boys and men.</note> and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> in unſeemly <hi>veſtures and voyces.</hi> I confeſs their <hi>Common-Prayer is my burden,</hi> by reaſon of its <hi>defects and diſorder,</hi> and the rudeneſs of the Miniſterial Method. I ſtand convinced, it ought to be altered; yea, ab liſhed,<note place="margin">See the Epiſtle to the Liturgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conſidered.</note> by reaſon of its Symetry to the <hi>Romiſh Maſs,</hi> ſuperſtitious Order, and unſutableneſs to Solemn Publick Prayer; yet I muſt confeſs, I find in it no <hi>Matter</hi> to which (on a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table interpretation) a ſober ſerious Chriſtian may not ſay, nay, can deny his <hi>(Amen:)</hi> And though I diſtaſte the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thod,</hi> I cannot diſown in it the <hi>eſſential Form of Prayer;</hi> (viz.) <hi>A calling upon God in the Name of Chriſt.</hi> That <hi>Set-Forms of Prayer are uſed,</hi> is an Act and Argument of <hi>weakneſs;</hi> that they are <hi>impoſed on Gods Church</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> is an Act (I cannot acquit) of <hi>wickedneſs:</hi> And that this defective diſorderly Form, is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,</hi> yea, by <hi>forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> returned</hi> into the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I fear will be found an Act and Argument of <hi>wilfulneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods mind;</hi> yet neither the <hi>one,</hi> nor the <hi>other,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it ceaſe to be <hi>Publick Solemn Pray r;</hi> nor do I ſee on what ground I can deny, or refuſe my <hi>(Amen)</hi> to what is prayed for, becauſe I know there are many things wanting to the Church, which are not, not indeed can be by this Form expreſſed; or not joining deſires to God with (and as a Member of) his Church, becauſe they are rudely and unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly expreſſed; whil'ſt the irregularity of that common Order, is no Bar to Gods acceptance of my more regular <hi>(Amen)</hi> thereunto given.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Departure from Babylon,</hi> is the indiſpenſable <hi>Duty,</hi> and will be the <hi>property</hi> of all, <hi>whoſe names are written in the Lambs Book of Life;</hi> but the Object muſt be <hi>Babylon</hi> in the very abſtract; <hi>Setting the mark of the Beaſt on them who partake with her,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 13.8, 17, 4, 13, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>bearing in her hand the Cup of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination,</hi> and ſo appearing to be <hi>formal spiritual Aegypt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sodom:</hi> I cannot believe every or any Society retaining ſome <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                           <desc>•••…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſtures,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> with a proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52790:17"/>
and apparent <hi>receſſion from Babylon,</hi> can be the Object thereof; and the laſt of theſe, is the <hi>capacity of Englands Church:</hi> Certainly the <hi>Temple of the Lord</hi> is not to be diſowned, or renounced, becauſe it hath been ſometime <hi>trodden down by the Antichristian Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>vitiated</hi> by the ſeat of the Beaſt; when theſe are expelled, though the dirt of their tramplings, and ſtink of their ſeſſion remain behind them: My good friend, let it be ſeriouſly reſolved, is there no difference between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah? Rome,</hi> and a <hi>reformed Church?</hi> a profeſſed <hi>ſacrifiſing Prieſt,</hi> and a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Gospel,</hi> fondly affecting and retaining that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation? between a <hi>calling on the only true God, in the name of Chriſt,</hi> though in a defective, rude, confuſed, and unfitting order, and praying unto Saints and dumb Idols? between the <hi>diſorderly adminiſtration of the worſhip,</hi> for matter and form, Gods own appointment, and the <hi>Ordinance nullifying adminiſtration in an unknown tongue,</hi> to which the hearers cannot ſay <hi>Amen?</hi> and <hi>abſtraction,</hi> or <hi>alteration of the Elements</hi> beyond, yea contrary to Gods preſcription, or what the poſſibility of nature, and entity of the ordinance will admit? between <hi>Sacraments</hi> with ſome unwarrantable ſuperſtitious Appendants, and a <hi>Sacrifice expiatory for the quick and dead?</hi> muſt we depart from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> returned from <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon?</hi> though retaining the ſavour, ſome of the Manners and Cuſtoms, and an hankering mind to go back unto thoſe accurſed places? I pray God keep <hi>England</hi> (in her now retrograde motion) from going back to <hi>Rome,</hi> then (through his Grace) I ſhall not dare to renounce her <hi>Communion,</hi> though my ſoul mourn for her <hi>corruption:</hi> for ſo long as we enjoy in her the very <hi>matter,</hi> and <hi>eſſential form of Gods worſhip, and Ordinances,</hi> though in an humane, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, corrupt miniſterial method and order, with ſome vaine and needleſſe appendants of humane invention; we are not without confidence of Gods <hi>preſence,</hi> and a <hi>poſſibility of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> and we therefore are without a ſufficient ground for <hi>ſeparation, or non-communion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſid.</hi> 3d. Communion is no bar, but a help to refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note>Thirdly, let it be conſidered <hi>Communion with the Church,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52790:17"/>
under many, and great corruptions, is not inconſiſtent with zeal, care, and conteſt for reformation thereof:</hi> the <hi>deſigns of Hell</hi> may agree in the end, but diſagree in the means; but it is not ſo with the <hi>determinations of Heaven;</hi> the Devil may ſuggeſt and provoke the correction of <hi>ſin,</hi> by <hi>ſin;</hi> or make <hi>zeal to purity</hi> a <hi>ſpurre to ſeparation,</hi> and the <hi>ſhiprack of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> to, and <hi>in the Church;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.13, 14.15.</note> he can make the white Witch <hi>heale,</hi> what the black doth <hi>hurt;</hi> by him one Conjurer doth <hi>bleſse,</hi> what another doth <hi>curſe;</hi> the <hi>Angel of light</hi> doth often expel, and lay the <hi>Angel of darkneſſe;</hi> but yet they be both <hi>evil Angels;</hi> he ſticks not at, nor ſtirreth againſt <hi>Piety,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> provided it be but <hi>ſinful;</hi> he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent men go in a <hi>via lactea &amp; ſacra,</hi> to the place of woe; and ſteere by Conſcience (if erronious) to their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: but it is not thus with God, and the dictates of his holy Spirit; all his commands are <hi>competible;</hi> his Graces <hi>concatenated;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5, c. 7.</note> All the duties of a Chriſtian are to be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged without <hi>interfering, interruption,</hi> or <hi>deſtruction</hi> by one another; he alloweth not one <hi>ſinful ſtep</hi> in the way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, though paved with never ſo fair a <hi>pretence of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> if therefore his people ſtumble thereinto, they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and go back, if they will go to heaven; no one duty, at any time damps zeal unto another; they may be <hi>deſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> but never are <hi>oppoſita,</hi> different, but not contrariant one to another, the <hi>diſcords in true Religion</hi> do ever conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the cleareſt harmony, all extreams are equally odious unto the God of order; exceſſes finde no more acceptance with him, than defects in Religion; <hi>be not righteous over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much</hi> is a divine dictate (though many times unduly,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.16, 17.</note> and unjuſtly pleaded by men) as well as be not <hi>over-much wicked,</hi> Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> may not turn to the <hi>right or left hand,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 5.32.17.20.18.14.</note> depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the way of his Statutes: the true Chriſtian muſt walk <hi>in all well-pleaſing, in every good word, and work, and hate every evil way:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note> It hath been a ſcandalous Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy (from its very firſt being) of Chriſtianity, to ſay or ſuppoſe it doth direct its ſubjects to do <hi>evil, that good may come thereby:</hi> ſincere Saints are ever acted by the Spirit of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52790:18"/>
                     <hi>peace, and love,</hi> to ſeeke and zealouſly purſue, the <hi>purity of Gods worſhip in union with his Church;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 3.8, Reformation a duty.</note> zeal, care, and conteſts, for <hi>Reformation of Gods Church, and worſhip, ſubjected to the leaſt corruption,</hi> can never be denied to be the indiſpenſable duty of every Chriſtian: It is true, theſe are to be expreſſed and acted by <hi>all law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul,</hi> and <hi>only lawful means,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chro. 13.9.10, 11.</note> according to every mans <hi>place and capacity;</hi> the moſt dreadful <hi>ſhakings of Gods Arke,</hi> will not warrant <hi>Uzza</hi> to ſtep out of his place to ſtay it; nor will the greateſt <hi>ſanctity</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numb 16.</note> authorize <hi>Chora</hi> to uſurp the Prieſthood: It is not a more poor apology, than baſe, for the rebellion of <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abyram,</hi> that <hi>all the Lords people are holy;</hi> the God of holineſſe needs not, nor will he endure the help of our iniquities: theſe Cautions obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>endeavours for reformation</hi> can be by none omitted, or faintly purſued, without an inevitable contracting upon themſelves the guilt of thoſe corruptions, which remain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods Church and ſervice; for no rule (in reference to humane ſociety) is in Morality, or Divinity more true than this <hi>error, cui non reſiſtitur approbatur, veritas non quae non defenditur opprimitur, negligere quippe cum poſſis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbare perverſos, nihil aliud eſt quam fovere, nec caret ſcrupulo ſocietatis occultae qui manifeſto ſacinori cum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test deſinit obviare.</hi> Er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>r not reſiſted, is allowed, for <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence gives conſent;</hi> Truth not defended, is oppreſſed, for, <hi>Cowardize giveth falſhood the Conqueſt,</hi> to neglect when we can do it, to diſturb the wicked, is to cheriſh them, for <hi>concealment and indulgence is the guard of their deſigne,</hi> nor can he want a ſuſpition of ſecret conſpiracy, who can, but will not hinder iniquity; for ſuch <hi>Connivance is an act and argument of affection:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sam. 2.</note> let it be remembred old <hi>Elies</hi> ſin, by which he fell under the ſeverity of Gods wrath, was his <hi>not reforming the abominations of his ſons;</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Government of many pious Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> are blotted, with a but <hi>the high places</hi> (which the Temple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoted and frequented ſeemed not worth the heeding) <hi>were not taken away: Iſrael</hi> is charged with the prophaneneſſe of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52790:18"/>
Gods Sanctuary,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44.7.8.</note> by reaſon of the <hi>uncorrected neglect</hi> of the Keepers thereof, and the <hi>non-reſiſtance of falſe Prophets,</hi> is aggravated with a (<hi>the Prophets prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>cy lies in my name,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 5.31.</note> 
                     <hi>and the people love to have it ſo;</hi>) It is a matter of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a God of jealouſie, that his Church and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ſhip ſhould be overſpread with corruption, without the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>king, and expoſtulations of an Advocate for him;<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.16.</note> 
                     <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it, and it diſpleaſed him, that there was no judgment; and he ſaw that there was no man, and he wondred that there was no Interceſſor;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor 5.</note> the guilt of the inceſtuous perſon is by the <hi>neglect of diſcipline,</hi> charged on the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and the <hi>ſuffering the woman Jezabel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 2.20.</note> is the evil imputed to the Church of <hi>Thyatira:</hi> the light of nature, and Scripture leadeth every one in his <hi>place and capacity</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form corruption, and chargeth it on their conſcience, as a poſitive duty.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>damp zeal,</hi> or <hi>barre endeavours for reformation,</hi> and to <hi>blame,</hi> and <hi>violently ſilence Miniſterial rebukes, and argumentation, or popular petitions, ſupplications, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and murmurations,</hi> under and againſt the corruptions of Gods Church and worſhip, is <hi>irrational, and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> and the defence thereof by this plea <hi>(viz.)</hi> theſe <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions are confeſſedly conſiſtent with ſalvation; and ſuch which notwithſtanding the moſt ſerious and zealous repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do not, and profeſſe they dare not ſeparate from, or deny communion with the Church;</hi> is no other than helliſh divinity, and Bedlam Reaſon, beſt confuted by their wives rebukes of the Queene of S uts preparing her miſtriſs <hi>ſack poſsets</hi> in the common <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhbowles</hi> (not to mention a veſſel of more baſe imployment) or preſenting to the table his dainty Cates in a diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> licked by the dog, and wiped with her diſh-clout; the which though it be unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and unwholſome, is not <hi>poyſonous,</hi> and ſo directly deſtructive, as to drive them the houſe or table; ſo as to begge or ſtarve, rather than to eate or keep good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: ſuch as ſhall thus do, muſt needs proclaim themſelves <hi>ignorant of the reproving invective Miniſtery</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52790:19"/>
and Apoſtles; yea, of the Lord himſelf, when and whilſt they lived in Communion with the Church of the Jewes; the laſt of whom whipt the money-changers out of the Temple, when and becauſe he acknowledged it, his <hi>Fathers houſe of Prayer;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 2.16.</note> 
                     <hi>inſenſible of the ſad and ſevere judgments of God</hi> on <hi>Eli</hi> and his <hi>ſons</hi> for their uncorrected diſorder, which made Gods people <hi>loath the ſacrifices of the Lord,</hi> when they did not, nor durſt leave his Sanctuary; and on <hi>Solomon</hi> for building high places,<note place="margin">1 Kings 11.31.</note> though conſiſtent with the Temple of the Lord;<note place="margin">Ezek. 43.8.</note> and on <hi>Iſrael</hi> for building their poſts beſides his poſts, their Altars beſides his Altars, and ſetting up the Image of jealouſie in the Houſe of the Lord, which yet was not forſaken by him or his people: <hi>and unaffected with the nature and holineſs of God,</hi> who will have <hi>holineſſe</hi> written on all the veſſels of the Sanctuary, and the very bridles of the horſes;<note place="margin">Zack. 14.20.</note> and will have all things in his ſervice done <hi>decently and in order,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.40.</note> becauſe he is a God <hi>of order, and not of confuſion;</hi> when <hi>Corruption in Gods Church and worſhip</hi> can be denied to be <hi>ſin,</hi> I will allow and adviſe Gods Miniſters to be <hi>ſilent;</hi> and when they grow <hi>ſubſtantiall, and vitiate their ſubject,</hi> I will allow and adviſe the <hi>Members of the Church to ſeparate,</hi> but till then I dare not give my conſent, or Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance unto the one, or the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reformation and Seperation</hi> (whereof <hi>voluntary non Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> is the privative part,<note place="margin">Seperation no act of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> and the firſt formal act) <hi>though</hi> (by the groundleſs Calumny of the enemies to the one, occaſioned by the raſh inconſiderate zeal of the other) <hi>they are confounded, are in themſelves vaſtly different, and indeed inconſiſtent, and deſtructive each to other;</hi> as much as is the <hi>Cleanſing, and caſting away a veſsel; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and parting from an houſe,</hi> this is <hi>duty,</hi> but that is <hi>horrid iniquity; ſchiſmes</hi> in the Church are <hi>dangerous, and diſgraceful,</hi> but ſchiſmes from the Church, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>deſtructive and damnable</hi> to the ſubjects thereof; the <hi>purity of Gods Worſhip</hi> muſt be purſued in <hi>unity with the Church; and Communion</hi> is implied in all endeavours for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52790:19"/>
                     <hi>Reformation; deſertion</hi> doth declare <hi>deſtruction,</hi> not <hi>repair</hi> of the houſe is deſired, and deſigned; which of us leave our houſes becauſe not ſo convenient, handſome or health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as is deſired? or forſake our food becauſe of a ſlovenly Cook or Carver? the Scripture doth detect much corruption in Gods Church, and the zeal of many unto the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, provoking and purſuing it unto death, or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deep diſtreſſe, without the leaſt direction unto, or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>ſeparation</hi> or <hi>non-communion;</hi> but with a moſt plain and clear charge and direction to the contrary; Chriſts A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, (as moſt zealous Reformers) did often, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with much authority rebuke and reſiſt the diſorder of the Churches, and corrupt adminiſtration of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet were ſo farre from approving or adviſing ſeparation, that they have branded the ſubjects thereof, with theſe and the like odious epithites, <hi>they were not of us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 2.19. Jude 19. Heb 10.25.</note> 
                     <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore went out from us, theſe are they who ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſenſual, having not the ſpirit,</hi> and taxeth the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary non-communicants with a defect, <hi>forſake not the aſſembling of your ſelves as the manner of ſome is.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without trembling conſider, the circumciſed Sects in the Church of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> are charged to have <hi>left the head,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Coll 2.19.</note> by <hi>leaving the body,</hi> in which <hi>all the joynts are knit together to the nouriſhment of the whole;</hi> I cannot but aſſent to that maxim as moſt true, <hi>ex Eccleſia nulla ſalus,</hi> the Church is <hi>Gods Arke of ſalvation,</hi> out of which none but mad men will leap, or leave it, on pretence of purging it, or putting out of it unclean birds and beaſts: in this caſe of conteſt for <hi>Reformation, and communion with the Church under ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great corruptions;</hi> I muſt ſay as our Saviour of the leſſer, and more weighty matters of the Law,<note place="margin">Luke. 11.42.</note> 
                     <hi>theſe things ye ought to have done, and not leave the other undone;</hi> for <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> are extreams equally odious, and ominous to Reformation; is it not obvious to every wiſe obſerver, that the Devil and wicked men, do make the one the advantage of the other; and caſt the odium, and direct the force of each (as the turn cometh, and opportunity
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52790:20"/>
ſerveth) againſt ſuch who (ſteering by Scripture Compaſſe) deſire (according to their capacity) to guide Gods Church, and themſelves in her, between theſe two dangerous Rocks into the Haven of reſt and holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Whileſt poor deſpicable I in our late years, in my place and Calling, withſtood our <hi>Church-waſting ſeparation,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſing piety, and purſuing purity in Gods Houſe and Ordinances, were (prejudiced (unto an high and open per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of me) by their own fancy that I <hi>aſserted and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced the ſuperſtitions and diſorders of our Church;</hi> by the return whereof God hath convinced them of their raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſtrained them to correct their miſtake of his unworthy reproached ſervant: and now God (bleſſed be his name) having <hi>animated me with zeal for perfect, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Reformation,</hi> and acted me in my place and ſphere (as a Miniſter of the Goſpel) to debate the obligations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, beyond my mean abilities, or the logical reply of the adverſaries thereof; (who bear away the victory by a <hi>thou lieſt Bellarmine;</hi> and have confuted me <hi>argumento ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culino,</hi> enforced by the ſevere moderation of authority; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by the ſuggeſtion of Treaſon and Sedition ſecretly whiſpered, and generally charged againſt me, whoſe loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty is moſt legible by both active and paſſive characters) and who have in all the writings which bear my name, declared my abhorrency of Sedition and popular tumults,) and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bleſſed me with an heart, and opportunity to withſtand and witneſſe againſt the deluge of Superſtition and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which breaking over, and bearing down ſacred banks, doth (to our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and ſhame) again overflow our Church and Nation; how many do now dream I will indulge, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>Separation;</hi> or at leaſt by my <hi>voluntary non-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (the firſt act thereof) give ſome countenance unto it? as if between theſe there were no <hi>medium;</hi> but that the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the one,</hi> muſt neceſſarily <hi>generate the other,</hi> give me therefore leave to tell you, and by you to tell others (in me concerned) I cannot but withſtand the <hi>one,</hi> with abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of the <hi>other;</hi> and keep my diſtance from <hi>ſeparation,</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52790:20"/>
whilſt I deſire and endeavour, to ſtave off <hi>Superſtition;</hi> leſt I Shipwrack my ſelf, or others, on either rock;<note place="margin">Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration ſtrengthen each other.</note> I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and our Church hath experienced the ſame, that as <hi>Superſtition, Corruptions and diſorder in Gods houſe and worſhip do</hi> (and therefore call for the zeal and rebukes of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and carefull Remedy by his Majeſties Prelates, by him entruſted with the Eccleſiaſticall good of his Subjects) <hi>very much harden men of ſtrong affections, and weak Judgements to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</hi> furniſhing them with a clamourous accuſation, who diſcerne not the proper and genuine cauſe of their ſinfull Shiſme, but readily father,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3, 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19.20.21.</note> (what the Apoſtle hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be) the brat of their own luſt, on any thing which beareth relation thereunto; though but a remote, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall occaſion thereof: ſo <hi>non communion and ſeparation,</hi> is the grand <hi>Removal,</hi> and moſt <hi>Plain ruin to reformation,</hi> that ever could be deviſed: <hi>Subverting</hi> the houſe on pretence and inſtead of ſweeping it; as if an houſe forſaken, and pulled aſunder (one running away with a poſt, another with a beam, to patch up their own ſelf-founded fabricks) were ever like to be purged, and preſerved from uncleaneſs and diſorder: (my good friend) take notice of this; God determined, and his people deſerved the deſtruction of the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before thoſe who feared God fled from among them, or forſooke them. <hi>Babylon is fallen, ſhe is fallen,</hi> was the voice uttered by the Angel, before, <hi>Come ye out of her my people</hi> was ſounded to the Saints which follow the Lamb; <hi>Conſervation</hi> is the end of <hi>burdenſome Communion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.2.7</note> and <hi>carefull Reformation;</hi> but <hi>diſſolution</hi> is the moſt certain ſequell of <hi>deſertion;</hi> It is Gods and muſh be his peoples laſt work to <hi>depart from and forſake his Sanctuary;</hi> he ſtayes long with a grieved ſtriving Spirit: and ſtands on the very threſhold, with a wooing expoſtulation, <hi>Be thou inſtructed O Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
                     <hi>leaſt my Soul depart from thee, and I make thee deſolate:</hi> (the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iſſue of departure) let it be ſeriouſly reſolved: did not <hi>Corah</hi> in his ſeparating from the Camp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> gathering a Congregation out of the Congregation: and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Sectaries among the primitive Chriſtians, ſtrike
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52790:21"/>
at the foundations, and ſeek to ſubvert the very ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from whence they ſeparated? and do not the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſome principles of the ſemi-ſeparating (as they would be deemed) ſelfe conſtituting Independents of our age, determine a non-entity; by the non-formality of a Church in <hi>England,</hi> and ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the very foundation thereof, and ſo condemn the very generation of the juſt, who have lived and dyed members thereof, yea Martyrs to the truths of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus Chriſt, againſt Papall, as well as Pagan power and errors? The Anabaptiſts in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> have not been more odious, and obſtructive to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> reformation; then the Church gathering ſeparatiſts of all Sects have been retarding unto a retrogradation of that in <hi>England:</hi> in that the odium of their ſchiſms ſeconded with <hi>ſeditien,</hi> and centred in <hi>Rebellion,</hi> un o <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicide,</hi> with the confuſion and ſubverſion of our Church and Kingdom, is (moſt ſadly and ſhamefully, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly) imputed to all, who with humble and peaceable ſpirits, deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and endeavour the caſting out <hi>corruption and diſorder,</hi> from Gods houſe and ordinances; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectes on the work of reformation it ſelfe, as if their proper genuine and natural parent.</p>
                  <p>The reformation of the Church is a duty incumbent on every man and member thereof;<note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means</note> onely it muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued in their <hi>places and capacities,</hi> by <hi>juſt and lawful means</hi> without ſchiſm from, (or if poſſible) <hi>in the Church,</hi> or ſedition <hi>in the Common-wealth,</hi> both which my ſoul ever did abhor as diſgraceful to <hi>Religion,</hi> diſhonourable to <hi>God,</hi> and deſtructive to <hi>Reformation:</hi> I never did, nor yet can allow, or adviſe other means of reformation then <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial admonition</hi> to the Church, <hi>Logical diſpute,</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological argumentation,</hi> and <hi>redaurgtion</hi> among equals; humble propoſal, petition, and ſupplication to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors with a <hi>patient,</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſe attendance</hi> on their pleaſure and on God acting the ſame; ſuch as receive Kings as <hi>nurſing Fathers to the Church,</hi> will rejoyce in them as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> much more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52790:21"/>
as <hi>profeſſedly reformed;</hi> and with all peaceable <hi>ſubmiſſion,</hi> embrace ſuch degrees of Reformation of the extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call order, and miniſterial method of Gods worſhip (en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the ſubſtance in the eſſential form thereof) as they will allow, untill God encline their hearts to allow what himſelfe expecteth, and his people deſire: ſoberly purſuing the <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> with joy in the <hi>eſſe of Religion,</hi> and in <hi>communion with the Church,</hi> waiting on the truth of <hi>Gods ordinances,</hi> quietly attending their Superiors for <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>regularity of diſpenſation;</hi> I find not that the men fearing God in <hi>Iudah,</hi> did tumultuouſly tumble down the high places, nor turn away from Gods Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple becauſe of them; yet their ſtanding was the ſtain of Government to their reforming Kings, to flye out of Gods houſe, or in the face of Gods Vicegerents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own appointments are adminiſtred by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in order to his ſervice unſuitable, and to us offenſive, is a frowardneſs which God cannot nor will not admit, or indulge in any of his children. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial reproofs and admonitions, and vulgar mournings and murmurations,</hi> are loud alarums to God and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men, and ſtrong enforcements of Reformation: <hi>preces &amp; Iacrymae</hi> ever were and ſtill are the onely wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the truly Godly,<note place="margin">Our ſtate and time calleth for an higher degree of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> under and againſt the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of juſt authority, and lawful Princes, ſuch as God hath in his mercy, and by his miraculous provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence reſtored to our Church and Nation. I am afflicted by, and aſhamed of the ſlow progreſs, and ſhameful retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation of <hi>Englands Reformation,</hi> under and againſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, national, ſolemn, ſacred bonds (whoſe obligation will abide before God, and conſcience, though the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations thereof may be interdicted by men) <hi>If Calvini</hi> in his days could ſay, (<hi>If Godly Religion had flouriſhed in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>till that day (the time of Queen</hi> Mary <hi>her Raign) there ought to have been an order of ſervice better corrected,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſtle to the Ch. at <hi>Frankford</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and many things quitte taken away.</hi> Can we without grief conſider our Church hath enjoyed true Religion more then eighty
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52790:22"/>
years ſince that time: and yet we ignorantly continue, and violently contend for that order of ſervice, as if aſhamed to <hi>give place unto better things:</hi> yet, I dare not deny her to be a reformed Church, or as ſuch, decline Communion with her: in, and for whom the Lord hath emminently appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and out of whom he hath gratiouſly purged all things <hi>venentous</hi> and <hi>deſtructive</hi> (though ſome things <hi>nauſeous,</hi> and <hi>distaſtfull,</hi> were continued, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into her) having defended her againſt the Spaniſh Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ado, and Popiſh Conſpiracy by Gunpowder, and other agitations, and attempts of Papall power and Antichriſtian rage; with an Almighty hand and outſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Arme. I do beleive the <hi>infancy of Reformation</hi> might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in, and grow up under that order of <hi>divine ſervice</hi> which the <hi>adult</hi> eſtate thereof ought to caſt off, as puerile and unſutable: Firſt degrees were matter of <hi>Comfort,</hi> though not of <hi>Content</hi> to ſuch who ſeek the ſimplicity of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: <hi>remaining dreggs</hi> ought to be diſcharged, and I doubt not God will (notwithſtanding mens averſneſs, and oppoſition) in due time effect it: In the mean time, i ſee no reaſon, to refuſe to drink becauſe my waters are pudled or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an unclean Veſſel, and I can come by no purer: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining degrees of Reformation muſt be ſo purified, that thoſe obtained, may not appear to be <hi>diſowned</hi> or <hi>deſpiſed:</hi> though our order of Divine Service be a <hi>Roman dregge</hi> of ſome dangerous diſtaſtfull influence, yet it is not <hi>Popery;</hi> ſhall we not bleſſe God, and rejoyce in <hi>England</hi> as brought out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> though ſome <hi>Babyloniſh Veſtures, Rites,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> which ought to be abandoned, are yet retained? I conceive them ingratefull for the <hi>purity obtained,</hi> who run out of Gods, houſe, for the <hi>Corruptions continued, and obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> I cannot but repute them <hi>over forward,</hi> who ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the <hi>Substantials of true Religion,</hi> and Chriſts Inſtitutions, becauſe of ſome <hi>rude Rough Appendants:</hi> ſhall we not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Gods mercy in affording us, and humbly uſe the truth of Gods word becauſe tranſmitted unto us with ſome humane traditions? and the ſubſtance of his own wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52790:22"/>
celebrated in a diſorderly way, and method, with ſome fooliſh Appendants, of mens inventions? (My good friend) my zeal, care and conteſts for Reformation of this poor Church, have coſt me dear: yet (if God ſuffer the Charge to riſe as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as did that of my nameſake by the unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of King <hi>Joaſh</hi>) not one mite too dear: I bleſſe God however my paſſions worke, I ſee no cauſe to repent my bargain: I pray God glorifie himſelf, and edifie his people by my bonds; onely I muſt profeſſe to all that fear God, I ſee no ſufficient cauſe to ſatisfie my Conſcience, or to plead before my God, on which to refuſe <hi>Communion with her,</hi> and attendance on <hi>Gods ſolemn publique worſhip under her rude Miniſterial method;</hi> for that duty is not warantably ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded by the <hi>iniquity of another man;</hi> my ſufferings, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſin, (under which I mourn, becauſe I cannot mend it) muſt not turn me out of Gods way, to the right or left hand; ſuperſtition, and ſeparation, muſt be ſhunned as Rocks equally dangerous to Gods Church and worſhip: the <hi>prophaneſſe of this and its Subjects</hi> muſt not drive me: nor the pretended <hi>purity and piety of the other,</hi> and <hi>its Subjects</hi> allure or draw me unto the <hi>poſitive evil</hi> of ſeparation, or <hi>privative evil</hi> of voluntary non-Communion; I pray and hope God will keep me upright under, and againſt all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, from falling into the extreams of our unhappy age and Church; and yet give me to ſee the purity of his worſhip in Union and Communion with his Church here on earth; or poſſeſſe me with his undefiled, unſtained glory in Heaven; for from the one I dare not depart untill I arrive at the other; leaſt by ſhipwarck I ſhould be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of both.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Let it be conſidered,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conſi. 4th.</note> 
                     <hi>Scandall is an argument of no ſtrength, when pleaded to ſuperſede or condemn a poſitive duty; Jobs</hi> friends,<note place="margin">offence no argument, in this caſe.</note> (like miſerable Comforters) were no little Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, that he would not from his <hi>Croſſe condemne himſelf as wicked;</hi> nor <hi>brand himſelf with Hippocriſy in his paſt piety,</hi> to which they laboured to compell him, by a right Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical, rather then Logical argument. (though not fully
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52790:23"/>
aſſerted) they that plow iniquity, &amp; ſo we wickedneſs, reap the ſame;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.4.5.26.19.42.7.</note> ſorrow is the fruit of ſin; yet Job well knowing the <hi>Proſperity of the wicked,</hi> and that <hi>God trieth the righteous,</hi> would not let go his integrity; Nor to juſtifie them, would he let his lips condemn himſelf, but made his appeal to God his witneſs on high, and record which is above; who interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to moderate the Queſtion,<note place="margin">Mark. <hi>2.23.</hi> ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</note> diſcovered their fallacy and determined they had not <hi>Spoken of him the thing which was right, as did his ſervant Job;</hi> The Jewes were offended that the Diſciples <hi>plucked the ears of Corn on the Sabbath day</hi> (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God for reſt) and that our Saviour <hi>on that day healed:</hi> yet our Saviour <hi>mattered not their offence as of any weight,</hi> but juſtified the facts by the poſitive duty of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving mans natural life;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 13.15.16.17.</note> If the <hi>Circumſtantials of the firſt Table</hi> muſt give way to the <hi>Subſtantials of the Second table of the Law;</hi> and if <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>humane,</hi> muſt give place to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine command, and authority;</hi> much more muſt the <hi>offence of a brother,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 5 29.</note> vail to <hi>obedience</hi> to the will of God: In pleaſing men, God muſt not be diſpleaſed: every man muſt therefore <hi>pleaſe his neighbour for his good to edification.</hi> but to pleaſe a brother by omiſſion of poſitive duty (which is formal,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2.</note> fearfull iniquity) is (by ſinfull ſtrengthning his propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">Scandal is not to be ſlighted.</note> or Error) <hi>aedificare in Gehennam,</hi> to edifie both to Hell, from which the Lord deliver me. Scandal is indeed an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of more weight (when duly and fitly pleaded) then to be ſlighted or ſuperſicialy evaded: <hi>not to offend a weak brother,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1.</note> is charged as a duty: we who <hi>are ſtrong ought to bear with the infirmities of the weak,</hi> and not to <hi>pleaſe our ſelves!</hi> Its <hi>good not to eate or drink, nor do any thing whereby thy brother is ſtumbled,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.21.</note> 
                     <hi>offended or made weak,</hi> are Divine directions and Goſpell rules: fearfull is the ſin of a Willfull Scandal, for that it is nor onely a ſnare by which a Brother is entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and laid on the rack of a Scrupulous conſcience, and tortured betwen his own doubts, and the contrary practice of the pious profeſſing obedience to Gods will, But alſo a ſtumbling-ſtone, occaſioning to him certain ſin; by either acting under his own doubts and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52790:23"/>
againſt his own apprehenſions induced by the bare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of another, or by uncharitable cenſureing his brother, in what is to him lawfull, and without his own liberty and power to do, or not to do it; this is therefore repreſented to be the <hi>deſtruction of the work of God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom</hi> 4.20</note> againſt this ſign our Saviour hath denounced a moſt ſad doom, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe litle ones, it were better for him a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and he were drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in tthe depth of the Sea:</hi> the dread hereof hath ſeized on my ſpirit, in my preſent ſtate and Caſe, that though it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lawfull,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.8.</note> could I without ſin withdraw from publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſolemn worſhip, in an unfitting order, I would on ſence of Scandal do it, Scandall is of force, and fitly pleaded to ſuperſede or condemn an action in it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and ſo within a mans own power to do, or not to do it;<note place="margin">ſcandal is of force in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diffrent.</note> for or againſt which the conſcience may be aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a ſeemingly religious reaſon; ſuch was the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or not obſerving a day, the <hi>eating</hi> or not <hi>eating of ſome kind of meates,</hi> or <hi>meates offered unto Idols,</hi> and the like things, which in the Primitive Churches, and times of Chriſtianity, the Apoſtles (during the honourable obſequies of the expired law, which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and yet ſeemed, to charge them as duty, or forbid them as iniquity) determined indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and directed Scandall of the weak as the caſting graine in the aequilibrious minde of a man (ſatisfyed in conſcience) as to the doing, or not doing the ſame; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by guiding us in all things and caſes of the like nature; for the indifinite Univerſal, <hi>Eat, drink,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> 
                     <hi>or any thing that may Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize, offend, or weaken a brother,</hi> adviſed in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.21. muſt be reſtrained to this ſpecies, and things of this kind: For what is poſitively forbidden, or commanded, muſt not at any mans pleaſure be done, or left undone: ſimple ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal hath no ſtrength. To plead <hi>we are offended,</hi> and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a reaſon, at leaſt ſeemingly religious, is a moſt ſimple plea:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling and a Rock of offence to many;</hi> and yet he muſt be preached and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52790:24"/>
                     <hi>profeſſed unto bonds, and death it ſelf.</hi> Such as in my caſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſcandal and offence, I muſt adviſe and intreat to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect their thoughts, and take heed they do not miſtake the caſe, and miſtake the queſtion, and thereby take offence, where none is given: I confeſs the miniſterial order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of publique worſhip and prayer, is <hi>purely humane,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the power of the Miniſters thereof, and ſo indifferent, and ought not to be <hi>preſcribed or impoſed;</hi> when it is as in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon divine ſervice rude, confuſed, and diſorderly, its no leſs <hi>Scandalous</hi> to the ſerious Godly, then was the <hi>adminiſtration of the Sons of Eli,</hi> or <hi>confuſed acclamations of the Church at</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth; and ſuch on which if I out of choice, at liberty to enjoy a more ſerious and regular order, (according to the Kings gracious Indulgence granted in his Royal declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs,) ſhould attend, <hi>I</hi> could not but give offence to ſuch as ſeek the <hi>Simplicity of the Goſpell;</hi> and ſeem to them to allow, what I have concluded ought to be aboliſhed, and to build again what I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to deſtroy: for extirpation of every thing which is evil (though but extrinſecall, and in the miniſterial me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Gods ordinances) being the extent of zeale, and duty of every member of the Church to be endeavoured in his place and calling, (though however not under a ſpecial, ſolemn, ſacred obligation thereunto,) non-attendance on that order unto, and by embracing of more regular admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the ſame ordinances in Communion with the ſame Church, is the leaſt <hi>Act</hi> I could do to the enfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that end; I cannot beleive the pious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would have brought their Sacrifices unto the Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> (whoſe order made them loath the offerings of the Lord, which they durſt not with-hold) if they had enjoyed other Prieſts who would have offered more conformly to divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But my friend, this is not my caſe or Queſtion, but whether <hi>ſolemn publique Worſhip,</hi> which is my poſitive duty unto the ſanctification of the Lords day and as I am a member of Chriſts Catholick viſible Church, and cannot by reaſon of my confinement be enjoyed without my at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52790:24"/>
on that Irregular unſuitable method, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed order: may be warrantably ſuperſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on this ground and reaſon, my preſence at ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations is offenſive to ſome weake Brethren zealouſly affected to the ſimplicity of the Goſpell, were theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions abſtracted from, or oppoſed unto Gods worſhip, there were to me no caſe of Conſcience, but they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with it, as the unclean veſſel, or ill favoured car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with my food whereby I live) and therein I muſt profeſs it ſatisfieth not my conſcience, nor ſeemeth to me to be of weight, that I muſt offer my ſacrifice, though by the loathſom order of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons, or go to the Temple, though my way lye by the high places, or aſſemble and ſend up my prayer in Gods Sanctuary, though the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>jealouſie</hi> be ſet up in it, cannot be ſoberly denied; nor ought any to be thereat offended; and I muſt needs reſolve in the affirmative, for the ſuperadded vanities do not <hi>void Gods ordinance:</hi> nor will defect and diſorder, (with which my private capacity is not charged) <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my poſitive duty;</hi> I am not inſenſible that ſome will be ready to read <hi>my allowance of the ſame,</hi> in my <hi>attendance on it,</hi> unto the hardning of themſelves in ſin, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring themſelves in duty, concluding, <hi>Communion in the ordinances</hi> is a conſent unto the order: to ſuch I muſt ſay at <hi>their peril</hi> be it; this ſcandall is <hi>taken</hi> not <hi>given;</hi> this inference is more than the promiſes allow: the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Prophets, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, with the Churches in their time under their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great corruptions, was not, nor logically could be interpreted, to be an argument of <hi>countenance,</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation</hi> of them, or abatement of the zeale againſt them; nor did they thereby <hi>contraction themſelves the guilt thereof;</hi> the ſpider which diffuſed in wine, doth vitiate its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and make it deſtructive by the very act of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, doth ſpread his dirty webbs all over the Vine, and we ear the grapes thereof, without the leaſt of doubt, or danger: the Cities that ſuffer by all unfit matter in their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52790:25"/>
publike miniſtrations, attend the good inſtructions, and aſſent unto the due propoſals, petitions, or demands, rudely uttered by their Recorder: nor think they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerned in the broken, blunt, abrupt ſtyle, or confuſed indigeſted method of his diſcourſe: the extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal adjuncts, and miniſterial method of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, is charged on the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> not members of Gods Church: it may indeed add grief or pleaſure to the people, but voyds not the matter of Gods worſhip, or leaveth any guilt on them, who thereby receive, and celebrate it, but do not approve the ſame: the ſpider may indeed ſuck poyſon of the grape, and wicked men may make my duty an occaſion of their iniquity: but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other giveth thereto any proper caſualty: events, accidentalls are no arguments againſt my duty: theſe are not more damnable to them, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them, then they would be to me: if I by reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of decline my duty: my own ſorrow, nor other mens ſin, muſt never ſtave me off from poſitive duty: theſe ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſtones and ſcandalous inferences, do, and will ever lye in my way to Heaven: yea to my natural life: Chriſts ſheep muſt drink, and may be hurt by pudled waters: witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t participation in the polluting pudling guilt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chargeable on the Paſtors, and proud of the flock, none can be offended that I worſhip God,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44.</note> in the ſolemn publike worſhip of his people: nor can without wounding their own ſoul be offended that I do it in this order, (to me diſtaſtful not to Gods worſhip deſtructive) untill my liberty doth manifeſt it to be an act of choice, not of chance: if any hence infer and enforce a <hi>perſecuting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,</hi> and ſay <hi>theſe men may be compelled to that form of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they will not chooſe.</hi> I ſhall grant it: but adviſe ſuch to ſit down and conſider how this will ſound in Gods cares: or how themſelves will like it to be confined to <hi>unclean veſſels, and order, becauſe they can but will not chuſe in ſuch to eat their meat;</hi> The offence of any who are Godly will be my trouble, and their ſin: but the omiſſion of duty though
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52790:25"/>
but for a day will be my tranſgreſſion, as I dare not admit that, as a reaſon of this, and muſt adviſe it be not pleaded.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly. Let it be conſidered in ſteering this courſe,<note place="margin">Conſid. 5. This pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hout preſident.</note> uſing this liberty, and holding Communion with this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Church, under theſe very corruptions, and by atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on this very order of ſervice, and ſolemn pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip: <hi>I am not without the caution and conduct of the ſober, godly, learned promoters, and purſuers of a perfect and compleat reformation:</hi> the reformed Churches beyond the Seas and in <hi>Scotland</hi> obtained higher degrees of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and more purity of ordinances, then did <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> (for power and dominion the chiefeſt reformed Church) yet theſe never did diſown, or decline Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with her, nor adviſe any her Members thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet they did often rebuke and complain of her luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm haeſitation in the degrees of reformation obtained, and retention of thoſe corruptions which ought to have been expelled among our ſelves: <hi>Tindall, Hooper, Ridley, Latimer, Farrar, Whitaker, Cartwright, Baines, Sibbs, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, Rogers, Geree,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Ball, Langley, Hind, Nicholls,</hi> with many others, the non-conformiſts of <hi>Lincoln, Devon,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi>) beſides thoſe of our preſent age, and yet contemporary with us) all eminent Divines, and Holy men groaning under theſe retained corruptions, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, perſwading, and preſſing after (unto many and great ſufferings) a progreſs in reformation, (unto the pure primitive plaines and ſimplicity of Chriſts own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) yet lived unto their laſt breath in conſtant Communion with our Church, attending Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances under theſe very diſorders and irregularities: and did in many things adminiſter according to the form then &amp; now impoſed, and did diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt the <hi>non-communion</hi> of ſuch who loytered out the time of publike prayer, becauſe preſcribed and confuſed: and by preſs and pulpit plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the ſeparations of <hi>Brown, Barrow, Iohnſon, Canne,</hi> and their ſeparating followers, and adherents, or
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52790:26"/>
non-communicating abettors; as inferring that from the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> which it would not allow; theſe good men with zeal reproved the many <hi>Superſtitions</hi> continued: but ſtill denied them to be any ſufficient ground for <hi>Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> from which they ever kept the greater diſtance, as ſubverting the very foundation of the Church: and have plainly trodden this tract, in which we muſt travel, purſuing the purity of worſhip in Union and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not fear to profeſſe, theſe good men are the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns to me propoſed, (next to the prophets, our Lord Jeſus, and the Apoſtles) and cautionary boigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the guidance of my zeal for the perfection of <hi>Reformation,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and paſt the dangerous extreams of <hi>Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſtitions, diſorderly adminiſtrations</hi> of Gods ordinances, and <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring religion, ſubverting ſeparation,</hi> nor am I herein ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that our caſe (becauſe our capacity is ſo) is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent from theirs: onely I wiſh it to be obſerved, the diff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erence is graduall not Real, it lieth on the <hi>meaſure and mode,</hi> not in <hi>matter and Subſtance:</hi> they were bound to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour an extirpation of the <hi>ſame evil</hi> but not by ſo ſtrong an obligation: They were in the infancy, we are in the <hi>adult eſtate</hi> of Reformation, and muſt therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the <hi>puerilia,</hi> which were their pleaſure our ſhame: The nature and quality of the <hi>Corruptions,</hi> with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their expulſion were by them <hi>under diſpute,</hi> it has been determined, and that by an Authority (ſometime reputed juſt) and (whatever it will do in politiques) will in point of conſcience yet abide a diſpute as to its lawfulneſs: they were entangled in the ſnares of educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and under the inſenſible yoakes of unſeaſonable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of <hi>approbation of,</hi> and promiſe to <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by this rude order</hi> and confuſed method: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the conſcience was awed, and the credit of Religion engaged them (by a burdenſome groaning ſpirit) to bear what they did not ſee how they could regularly be releaſed from: from all which we are free, and moſt ſtrictly tyed by contrary obligations: but neither they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52790:26"/>
nor we might <hi>out of our places and Capacities</hi> attempt a Reformation by any ſedition in the Republique, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Schiſme from the Church: Non-communion is no more warantable to us under the ſtrongeſt bonds to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation then it was unto them without them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an <hi>evil in it ſelf:</hi> The nature of the (retained, returned) corruptions were the <hi>ſame to them,</hi> they are to us, but to neither a juſtifiable reaſon for Non-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The adminiſtration of theſe good men in, and by this corrupt order, I can better, excuſe, then juſtifie, or intimate: I beleive <hi>extirpation</hi> to have been their duty as it is mine: and I ſee not how I may act, (though <hi>I</hi> as a private member may and muſt attend, aſſent and give my (Amen) unto right matter, in that order and method with thoſe corrupt Appendants I am bound to extripate: (Abſtinence from action being the leaſt, and firſt act of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation</hi>) in which the private Chriſtian is paſſive, pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſive, neceſſarily paſſive becauſe he cannot enjoy or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Gods worſhip in this indiſpenceable duty of holy convocation without it: <hi>I</hi> beleive the miniſterial me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of publique worſhip: to have been ſubject to their Judgement, and within their power as <hi>Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi> and <hi>Stewards of the miſteries</hi> of God himſelfe, full and formall Judges of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de and <hi>order</hi> of diſpenſation (not belonging to or charged on the private members, and objects thereof as to me: In both which reſpects (beſides that ſpecial capacity, in which <hi>I</hi> conclude all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our Church now ſtand by that ſpecial obligation which the tranſactions of providence in our unhappy times brought u on us, and our poſterities, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: I have elſe where profeſſed (and muſt ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, as the reſult of my moſt ſerious and deliberate thoughts) <hi>I can keep Communion under that form of worſhip,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſtle to</hi> Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>res.</note> 
                     <hi>whereby I cannot adminiſter and heartily ſay Amen to the Maſter of thoſe petitions which are put up in an order ſo confuſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous, and indigeſted, that it ſeems to me to be ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the gravity of the Church, whoſe mouth I muſt be, the ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the office whereby I miniſter, the ſanctity of the duty I am to perform, and the ſacred nature of the object to whom they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52790:27"/>
are preſented, that I dare not ſtand between God and his people with the ſame;</hi> I preſume no man will or can deny my capacity as a Miniſter, to differ from the capacity of a <hi>private Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and barr me againſt, or bind me unto, what the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a private member of the Church doth not barr againſt or bind unto: <hi>non-adminiſtration</hi> may ſubject me to a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my Miniſtry, when <hi>non communion</hi> cannot be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted nor excuſed; the <hi>reſtraint of that</hi> muſt not run me upon the <hi>ſin of this: I</hi> muſt (with the pious Iſraelite) <hi>leave my ſacrifice before the Lord</hi> (though with my ſouls abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of the prophane prepoſterous order of adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) when I dare not with <hi>violence ſnatch the fat of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and act according to the method of the ſons of Eli:</hi> I muſt not leap out of Chriſts fold, nor leave his paſtures, when trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down by others, becauſe I dare not preſent his ſheep with <hi>puddled waters:</hi> in the one I am paſſive by other mens ſin, in the other my action maketh the ſin mine own: Gods ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial worſhip muſt not be ſlighted or refuſed, becauſe the ſinful order of men attend it: <hi>Strait is the gate, narrow is the way which leadeth to life:</hi> whilſt I flie from the ſin of my <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> I may be, and muſt take heed <hi>I</hi> be not ſplit by flying into the ſin of a Member of the Church: that guilt may be charged on me in the <hi>collective</hi> body, which <hi>I</hi> muſt be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of in my perſonal capacity; where the Conſtitutions of men include, the righteous judgement of God will diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and diſcriminate;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4.</note> all particulars are included in an <hi>univerſal defection,</hi> but do not periſh by it: God will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to mark his mourners under Iſraels abominations in his worſhip,<note place="margin">Numb. 14</note> which they could not mend nor avoid: his <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s and <hi>Caleb</hi>'s, who follow him fully, ſhall nonfall ſhort of the land of promiſe,<note place="margin">Confid. 6.</note> though all Iſrael fall in the wilderneſs.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, Let it be conſidered, my communion with this Church under theſe corruptions is not more conſonant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the example of theſe good men of our Church,<note place="margin">Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under corrup. is conſonant to my own profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and the carriage of other reformed Churches, then unto my ſelf, who am (and I hope through divine Grace ſhall be) <hi>ſemper idem:</hi> ever ſince I knew any thing of Religion, and in any meaſure diſcovered the wayes of God and his people, I have <hi>grieved for, and conteſted againſt the corruptions of his Church,</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52790:27"/>
but avoided, abhorred, and oppoſed <hi>ſeparation from,</hi> yea a <hi>non communion with</hi> it, as the much greater evil; though pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with profeſſions of piety, and pretences of purity, to the ſeduction of the ſimple: ſuch as have ſate under my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery (now clouded by a righteous God) reveiwing their notes, and reflecting their thoughts on what I preached) will find a ſeries of rebukes and admonitions againſt <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and non-communion,</hi> though enticed by men ſeemingly the moſt holy, and pretences unto the greateſt purity and ſanctity: In the laſt Sermons that I preached from <hi>John</hi> 4.22. from our Saviours practiſe and pleading for the Church of the Jews, oppoſed to the Samaritans, I affirmed, <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Gods Church under many and great corruptions is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawful, but an indiſpenſable duty;</hi> the which I amplified by ſhewing the different nature of corruptions, as <hi>nouſeous</hi> and <hi>venomous,</hi> prejudicial to <hi>health and growth,</hi> or directly <hi>deſtructive,</hi> as <hi>intrinſecal</hi> and vitiating to the ſubject, or <hi>extrinſecal</hi> and converſant about the ſame; notwithſtanding which the ſubject remains the ſame, participation in which contracts guilt (as in offering ſacrifice to an Idol) or contracts no guilt to the Communicant (eating in an amicable friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip what is offered to an Idol) ſuch as put us out of a <hi>poſſibility of ſalvation</hi> (the only ground of ſeparation) or are therewith conſiſtent, impoſed by others, and ſo their ſin not ſufficient to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r our duty: all which were applyed to the <hi>Popiſh adminiſtrations,</hi> nullifying Chriſts Offices and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and ſo neceſſitating ſeparation, polluting by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation: and <hi>Englands corruptions</hi> grieving God and his people,<note place="margin">ſome 8. ſome 7. ſome 4. years now paſt.</note> but preſerving Gods worſhip in the ſubſtantial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and eſſential form thereof, and ſo not ſufficient to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede communion: If you look into the writings which bear my name in the world, you will find ſeparation, becauſe of corruption, condemned by reaſons, beyond what the moſt ſerious Church-gathering Separatiſts ever undertook to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, otherwiſe then by rage and reproach (the dialect of reſtrained luſt in that, as well as in this revolution): Read at your leiſure my <hi>Bethſhemeſh clouded: Saints zeal against ſinful Altars: Virtue and value of Baptiſme,</hi> written many years
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52790:28"/>
ſince, and you will ſee Mr. <hi>Crof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ons communion with the Church of England,</hi> is not repugnant to his judgement, more then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years ſince declared, and in thoſe very writings lately publiſhed (before and for which men have (by Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) brought my light under a buſhel) you ſhall find my <hi>zeal for Reformation</hi> conſiſtent to <hi>union and communion with the Church;</hi> nor did the force of oppoſing corruption drive me (as <hi>I</hi> might probably have done) to let fall any expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in favour of <hi>ſeparation:</hi> My logical caſuiſtical Conteſts for Reformation, do very plainly condemn, and proteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſchiſme and ſedition as thereunto deſtructive, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in my <hi>Anal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pſis</hi> to Doctor <hi>Gaudens Analyſis,</hi> my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Anſwer is thus concluded: <hi>Whatſoever ſhall be the establiſhment in the Church, though never ſo corrupt, yet whilſt conſiſtent with ſalvation, though it may occaſion to me ſuffering, and a ſuſpence of my Miniſtry by Gods Grace, it ſhall not effect on me, or ſuch on whome I have influence, Schiſme from the Church or a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistance of his Majeſties juſt Authority;</hi> And in my Epiſtle to the Lyturgicall Conſiderator conſidered (in which <hi>I</hi> urge my apprehended grounds for the alteration, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of the Miniſterial method of ſolemn publique prayer uſed in our Church) with a pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt for Communion under it, though againſt adminiſtration by it. <hi>I am ſo much affected to the peace of the Church, that I have of late preached, what (God aſſiſting I am reſolved for to practiſe (viz.) that many, and graet cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in Gods worſhip are to be grieved for, and patiently groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under, before Schiſme be conſented to, or ſeparation be conſulted: Provided nevertheleſſe I be paſſive, not active in them? I can keep Communion under that form of worſhip whereby I cannot adminiſter and heartily ſay Amen to the matter of thoſe petitions which are put up in an order ſo prepoſterous, and indigeſted, that I dare not ſtand between God and his people with the ſame;</hi> The liberty that <hi>I</hi> now purſue; (when obtained and uſed) is no more than a practice commenſing on theſe profeſſions, whereby they are made more legible, not more cenſurable than they were before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52790:28"/>My good friend, Theſe things conſidered, I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, when ever God ſhall mollifie the hearts of men, into whoſe hands he hath given my preſent liberty; I ſee not any reaſon (that I dare plead before the Lord, or reflect as a barre on my Conſcience) whereupon my ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Sabbaths may be ſweetned, and ſpent with comfort; my paſſage to the publique aſſemblie and worſhip, though in this order, and with theſe appendants which are bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome to my ſpirit, ſtanding open; and ſo my abſence being a voluntary act within my own power; If any man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the fear of God, can produce any, I ſhould be glad, for I fear to be charged with the omiſſion of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip, celebrated in Chriſt his Church, though with extrinſecal corruption, and in a rude Miniſteriall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which ought to be reformed; but will not excuſe me, though unforced, by the offence of ſome weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren zealouſly affected to the purity of Gods Houſe and Worſhip.</p>
                  <p>I am not inſenſible, that the Committee of diſcretion, will be no leſſe ready to call me <hi>fool,</hi> for ſteering this courſe, than they were for my entering the Liſts, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cement of Reformation, wherein I am deſerted by my more prudent brethren;) for that I here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſtrike oſt from that party, on whom my former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts did ſeem to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> me; But to them I muſt breifly anſwer, I am willing to be <hi>wiſe as a ſerpent,</hi> and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to keep <hi>my inno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> as a dove,</hi> ſo long as theſe do correſpond and agree, I have an heart to lodge them; but if <hi>prudence</hi> once ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ate or obſtruct <hi>duty,</hi> or <hi>guide</hi> into, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>guard</hi> ſin, I fear the <hi>ſerpent</hi> begins to wind too farre, and getting in the head, will wind in the body, and devour the <hi>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> that ſome who have been objects of my oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition (becauſe ſubjects of ſeparation) have in my preſent ſufferings embraced me, and ſhewed kindneſſe to me and mine, (beyond ſome more ſpecially charged with it, as their more particular duty.) I am very ſenſible, and thankfully acknowledge to God and them; and hope they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52790:29"/>
did not thereby deſigne to <hi>charme my zeal againſt what I ever cenceived to be ſin,</hi> I confeſs it hath been a check to my comforts, to conſider, ſome triumph in me and my ſufferings, becauſe oppoſed to the ſuperſtitions and prophaneſſe, (which they diſlike) who agree not with me in thoſe poſitive truths, which I have aſſerted; and will be turned in their hearts againſt me, when the ſame two-edged-ſword in my weak hand, ſhall be conſtrained to ſtrike their more civil, ſeemingly ſacred luſts; The <hi>Uſurer</hi> huggs, and hath the Preacher home to dinner, when he preacheth againſt the prodigal profuſal ſpending drunkard; who will hunt and hurry him out of the Pariſh when he ſhall preach againſt <hi>uſury:</hi> I cannot but tell you a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which here befell me; In my cloſe confinement three perſons, full of ſeeming zeal to piety and purity, ſtumbled into my chamber, and ſaluted me with this ſalutation, <q>we are ſtrangers to you, but in conſcience of our duty are come to viſit you as a ſufferer for Jeſus Chriſt;</q> to which kind and Chriſtian ſalutation I returned a ſhort admonition that we <hi>might endeavour to underſtand the truths of the Lord Jeſus, and labour to agree in poſitives, for I feared many rejoyced in my ſufferings as negative, and againſt what is groſſely evil,</hi> who would not embrace the <hi>truths I did contend for;</hi> on which theſe perſons zeal boiled over into this angry Taunt; <hi>what I warrant you, you are yet for the Church of England, and your pariſh Churches?</hi> to which I could not but Reply by way of advice, <hi>not to deny the being of the Church, nor renounce union and Communion with it, becauſe of the corruptions in it;</hi> but their zeal brake into rage, and railing, <hi>thou Antichriſt, wilt thou yet uphold the Beaſt and Whore of Rome? are you Antichriſt ſtill?</hi> with many more invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and expreſſions of outrage, which provoked me to give them this ſhort farewell, <hi>Freinds, reconcile your ſelves to your ſelves, am I a ſufferer for Chriſt, and yet Antichriſt? if you come not to viſit me, come not to vex me;</hi> to all diſſenting friends I cannot but by way of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52790:29"/>
thanks for all their kindneſſe, intreate them to <hi>ſtudy the truths of God I have aſſerted,</hi> and embrace not their force againſt <hi>me,</hi> but againſt <hi>both extreames;</hi> for that love will not laſt, which is founded in preſent contradiction, without conſent in poſitives aſſerted; <hi>Love the Truth, and me for the Truths ſake,</hi> then ſhall ye have the comfort of loving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth; It was my hope, and is my prayer, that our retrogradation in Reformation, would have made ſuch who departed from us, to reflect with ſeriouſneſſe (even unto Repentance) the experienced remorce of <hi>ſeparating, and Church confuſion,</hi> to which <hi>Church-gathering</hi> hath reſolved us; but if men harden themſelves to uphold their ſin, and ſtrengthen their party, (to the utter ſubverſion of this poor Church) and paganizing this Nation, they muſt give leave to truſt God with their <hi>love and kindneſſes,</hi> whilſt to my power I reſiſt their luſts; and let them know I cannot be a <hi>Martyr of Faction;</hi> I hope I can do all things, and ſuffer all things for the truth, and nothing againſt the truth: and muſt all my days purſue Reformation of Gods Ordinances in Union, and Communion with the Church, leaving my ſelf, principles, and practiſes to the judgment of God; knowing it is an eaſie matter for me to be judged and misjudged by men, and yet abide what I am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A ſervant to God, his Truth, and Church. Z.C.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Julij</hi> 20. 1661</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52790:30"/>
                  <p>AN APPENDIX To the foregoing LETTER: IN A LETTER, Written in anſwer to one, ſignifying to Mr. CROFTON, the Offence which was taken at his going to CHURCH, And being preſent at the COMMON-PRAYERS IN THE CHAPPEL IN THE TOWER OF LONDON.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52790:31"/>
                  <head>For Mr. <hi>Z. C.</hi> Priſoner in the TOWER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>DEAR BROTHER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOU cannot enough believe, how much your <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed</hi> publick Communion, with <hi>we know not whom,</hi> in the Ordinances, which they think cannot but be <hi>materially corrupt,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>that place,</hi> hath griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and alienated the hearts of the Godly; not only <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> but <hi>Miniſters:</hi> Defend it how we can, They cenſure it not only <hi>Impolitick,</hi> but <hi>Impious; hardning our Enemies, weakning our Friends, undoing your good Teſtimony,</hi> and <hi>giving away the CAUSE,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>aeque,</hi> if not <hi>aequaliter;</hi> as if you ſhould Read and Adminiſter the Form: They think there can be no Obligation of Duty, or Edification warranting the one, which may not alſo juſtifie the other. The matter of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and worſhip of <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſeems to be not only the <hi>objectum ad quem,</hi> but alſo <hi>per quibus,</hi> whether things or perſons; wherein they take it for granted, the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer</hi> is corrupt: As when you pray for Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, as <hi>Miniſters</hi> of a ſuperiour Degree (and indeed according to the new corrected Form of Ordination, of the only Holy Order and Inſtitution) wherein they are an Antichriſtian Order, &amp;c. Or if only the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Form were exceptionable, yet you judge the Nurſe may as well be bound in Duty and Neceſsity to give the Child his bread out of a Chamber pot, as ſhe her ſelf, or the Child feed themſelves out of it: Plead then you muſt neceſſity, for both or neither; and they expect you ſhould do th'other too <hi>(ſe defendendo)</hi> or elſe ſuperſede
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52790:32"/>
this for the time to come: But if you proceed, I perſwade my ſelf of that very many Brethren which are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the reſt, you will be alone in this; for they can with more patience brook to the preſent, where there be perſonal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in the Matter, than where there are circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, material Offences in the Form.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, Bound in your Bonds. <hi>P. E.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52790:32"/>
                  <head>For the Reverend Mr. <hi>P. E.</hi> to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to other Chriſtian Friends, and the Brethren of the Miniſtry concerned in his Letter, as ſcandalized at my Communion with the Church, in the Order of Service, by which I cannot adminiſter.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Good Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>GRace and peace abound; yours (no little aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine affliction) I received, I thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the grief, not only of Brethren in <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> but in the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> becauſe of (what you call <hi>renewed) my Communion, with their Church;</hi> in that Service by which I cannot adminiſter: and what is to me more greivous, their Cenſures of my act, as <hi>impolitick yea impious, hardning our enemies, weakning our friends, undoing my good teſtimony, and giving away the Cauſe:</hi> Sir, ſuch is my eſteem of the affections of the godly, that their grief muſt needs be mine: God is my witneſſe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, ſeek, ſtudy their joy; their grief for my duty, can only grieve me in by being groundleſs; whereby they wound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by wounding him whom God hath greived; and that by moſt bitter words, ſharper then Swords or Razors, <hi>hardning our enemies, weakning our friends,</hi> are eaſily borne, they are events by accident; beyond the nature and intent of the Act, or the intention of the Agent; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting from the wickedneſſe of the one, and weakneſſe of the other: to deem this Act, <hi>Impolitick,</hi> I take not ill; all my acts and writings have been ſuch in their account; the Cenſures of the Committee of diſcretion, are to me ſo common, that they paſſe on me as things of courſe;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52790:33"/>
branding with folly what could never be convinced of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but <hi>impious</hi> doth pierce mine intrails, to ſhun ſin hath been my ſtudy, my ſmart; did not piety bar may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, I could ſleep in as whole a skin as my more prudent <hi>Brethren;</hi> the fear of God, conſcience of duty, provokes this impious act; what a Monſter of man hath God made me? my courſe is nothing but contradictions, <hi>treaſonable loyalty; ſchiſmatical unity; impious piety:</hi> yet this is not all, <hi>an undoing of my good teſtimony, and giving away the Cauſe,</hi> and ſo an <hi>Apostate,</hi> can any thing cut deeper? be more clouding to my ſufferings? more deprive God of the glory thereof? it pierceth my ſoul to cry <hi>Lord judge</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and Brethren, <hi>my witneſſe is on high, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is above;</hi> I have charity for <hi>Jobs</hi> miſerable comforters; they ſpake well of God, though their arguing reproved not <hi>Job,</hi> for they ſpake with a miſtaken zeal; I believe they were Saints againſt whom <hi>Paul</hi> appealed; <hi>it is an eaſie thing for me to be judged of men, my judgment is of the Lord;</hi> The Lord ſtrengthen my patience under this moſt provoking temptation, that I may with ſobriety reaſon againſt clama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous cenſorious Brethren.</p>
                  <p>My good Brother, where is ſobriety? charity? is zeal for purity a <hi>Moſes</hi> Serpent, to devour theſe Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? <hi>Cave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why is my now attendance on ſolemn publick worſhip, branded to be <hi>renewed communion, with you know not whom?</hi> if you mean this of <hi>perſons individual,</hi> truly as to the moſt <hi>I know not whom,</hi> nor can I think you judge it neceſſary; I cannot in my firſt communion know it in any Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; is <hi>Church gathering</hi> become a Presbyterial principle? is it the work of every age? is ſeven, not ſeventy years an age? is <hi>non knowledge</hi> of Members a cauſe of <hi>non commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi> would not common charity make me know them to be a <hi>ſociety of Chriſtians?</hi> worſhippers of the true God in Jeſus Chriſt, and are they not hereby members of the <hi>Church Catholick viſible,</hi> particularly divided by local cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcription? or have we renounced this principle? is not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52790:33"/>
the Liberty of the Tower a <hi>particular Church,</hi> in a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial ſence as well as <hi>Chriſt Church,</hi> or <hi>Alhallows Breads ſtreet?</hi> If I communicate in theſe, muſt I not communicate with I know not whom? may I not <hi>hear the Goſpel preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and (in calling on God in the name of Chriſt, for things agreeable to his will) <hi>communicate</hi> with I know not whom? But why is my communion <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>newed?</hi> I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; I never ceaſed from; I never was cut off from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Engliſh Reformed Church, and its particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Aſſemblies:</hi> muſt Independents be verified in the falſe reproach, <hi>(viz.) Presbyterial Churches w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re gathered Churches?</hi> Presbytery interrupted was the Church diſſolved? and Communion abandoned? <hi>Cave.</hi>—We have diſowned, denied, determined ſin, and danger in theſe Notions; I have more charity than to think my ſelf out of <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> becauſe violently debarred from <hi>Convention</hi> with the particular Aſſemblies of the Reformed Engliſh Church. God having at length opened me a door of liberty to attend his ſolemn publick worſhip in this place, with this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, why is my acceptance, and uſe thereof clamorouſly condemned as an act not only <hi>impoliti k,</hi> but <hi>impious?</hi> do not you know this is the execution of a reſolution, neither <hi>new</hi> nor <hi>raſh?</hi> not <hi>new,</hi> for I thus determined, and thus <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in my youth,</hi> when piety was reproached by profane men, as <hi>Puritaniſm,</hi> and by the <hi>Browniſts</hi> as <hi>corrupt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:</hi> I thus <hi>determined,</hi> and <hi>declared in my publick Miniſtery,</hi> and preaching for Reformation: I thus deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in all my <hi>late diſputes and writings;</hi> whileſt I was at liberty I thus <hi>practiſed on accidental occaſions;</hi> I (herein convinced, and hereof perſwaded) <hi>prayed the liberty I now enjoy,</hi> the firſt day I was committed priſoner to this place, and have ever ſince petitioned to enjoy it: this act you know is not <hi>raſh,</hi> but the reſult of mature and deliberate thoughts, beſides what hath paſſed between God and mine own ſoul; I have heard and weighed the objections of <hi>ſeparating</hi> as well as <hi>reforming brethren;</hi> and after many expoſtulations I have (you know it) ſtated my Caſe of Conſcience, drawn up my
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52790:34"/>
reaſons, communicated them to Brethren, and Chriſtian Friends; craved a <hi>Confutation</hi> from more than one; prayed fraternal Correption, by ſolid and ſerious Argumentation; and profeſſed a readineſs to hear, and obey Conviction: I wonder after all this, and Nine Months time to have correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, convinced my Judgment; I ſhall be cenſured for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to Act, and you ſhould now call for an Apology.</p>
                  <p>Dear Brother, How long ſhall I complain? when ſhall I be known, and dealt with as a Brother? Is it fair Play to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, and not reprove? To condemn, and not confute? Will you neither convince my Conſcience, nor be content with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cenſures, to ſee me obey it? Are you angry to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on, and yet expect I ſhould live by an implicite Faith; and forbear what is to me a poſitive Duty, on this bare Reaſon, <hi>The Brethren will be displeaſed?</hi> Let me ſay it without Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs or Levity, <hi>Be not wiſe overmuch:</hi> The Offence of Brethren hath its place and weight in my Soul; but muſt be well grounded, before it counterpoize Conſcience of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, indiſpenſable Duty.</p>
                  <p>I well underſtand not the Epithites which vilifie my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Act, becauſe they are general, and without Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>That it is <hi>Impolitick,</hi> I may not deny; I have ever been eſtranged to, and at enmity with the Brethrens Policies and Fancy: If they had in ſome things been as <hi>fooliſh</hi> as ſilly I, God might have had more <hi>Glory,</hi> Truth more <hi>Strength,</hi> the Church more Purity and Order, my ſelf more Liberty; their Comforts I know not, nor will adventure to judge: What Policies this Act muſt relate unto, I know not; unleſs, it be the <hi>strengthning,</hi> and ſo <hi>juſtifying</hi> thoſe <hi>Schiſms</hi> which ſupplanted, ſubverted our Reformation, by thoſe <hi>Seditions, Rebellions, Treaſons,</hi> which have made it Odious, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized the endeavours thereof; that the moſt Upright, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent among us, are preſſed under it. If Brethren were ſenſible, That my Zeal for Reformation is reproached, repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and my ſelf, thus oppreſſed by theſe Schiſms; they would not ſure think it <hi>Policy</hi> to ſtrike hands with them; or <hi>Impolitick,</hi> to appear really, as well as verbally againſt them.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52790:34"/>
God knoweth I may not long ſpeak, let me ſpeak freely: Truly Brother, fooliſh I, think it <hi>aque,</hi> and <hi>aequaliter poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> for ſerious ſober Reformers, to unite with <hi>Non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating, Separating, Congregational Brethren,</hi> in the Church-confounding, nullifying principles and practiſes: As for our late <hi>King-Killers</hi> to cry up the <hi>COVENANT</hi>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the Quarrel of the Parliament, with the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> Confound 62. with 52. and you may reconcile 48. to 43. and ſoon return to 48. again: Agree theſe in <hi>Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> and divide them in <hi>Civils</hi> if you can. I wiſh I could not ſcent ſome Brethren (offended at my Act) as tainted already in their Civils: But I am a Fool, be it ſo; yet a Fools Bolt is ſoon ſhot. If <hi>Presbyters</hi> will wiſely ſerve Gods providence, and do his Church proper Service, Now it is their Time, and Buſineſs to witneſs Corruptions <hi>circa cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum publicum,</hi> will not warrant <hi>Non-communion</hi> with ſeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſeparation from a true Church, and ſuch I yet deem <hi>England:</hi> Correct this folly, and I may become wiſe; till then, I will through Grace, joy in my folly. I have obſerved indeed Gods, and the Kings Fools were never many: But truly, fooliſh I, could never judge it good Policy, That <hi>Non-communion, Separation,</hi> and the <hi>Sectarian Spawn,</hi> ſhould ſhroud themſelves, and be ſheltered by <hi>Non-conformity</hi> and <hi>Reformation:</hi> Hath not our dear-bought Experience taught us, That the Repute of being the Parent of theſe, hath been the <hi>Remora,</hi> and Retroverſion of that? Can we forget, how theſe, when in Power, did divide, divert, and deſtroy <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> Paganize all <hi>England,</hi> and plant <hi>One hundred and twenty gathered Churches,</hi> and thereby proclaim <hi>Entity,</hi> not <hi>Purity</hi> of the Churches, was their Quarrel? And ſhall we not now be ſo wiſe, as to diſown, and deny them, as a Baſtard brood: Now they are taken as Vagrants, and whip't up to <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> as their reputed Parents? Can we ever wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Relation more than by theſe affectionate embraces in this day of Diſcrimination? O! that my Brethrens Policy were ſo wiſe, as to conſider the Duty and Neceſſity of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> and thath they would pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52790:35"/>
the Honour and Benefit of <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> proteſting, and practiſing againſt <hi>Non-communion,</hi> in this day, when its Enemy doth confound and deſtroy this for the ſake, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of that. But whither am I gone? I muſt come back like a Fool, and tell you, I could never beat it into my Brains, That it was good Policy to run out of an unclean diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered Houſe, under pretence of cleanſing and regulating the ſame. My little will led me to abide in it, and by a Scrub Beeſom of a reproving M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſtry, ſuch as I can get, to bring the Duſt about mine Ears: I judge it prudent filth which hangs on my Cloaths, in a regular endeavour to get it out of my Houſe; I am miſtaken, if ever my Houſe will cleanſe it ſelf, if I run and call all others out of it: Once more, and all my wit is waſted; I am an Iriſh man, and never yet was ſo wiſe to lie in the Field, open to cold and wet, becauſe the Beaſts, not only ſtood, but unhandſomly dung d in my lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chamber? I have been uſed to Impoliticks, but am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be better adviſed. <hi>Impolitick!</hi> That is nothing, Fools may go to Heaven; but my Act is <hi>impious,</hi> This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be endured, without good Evidence, it is an high Charge: I pray, wherein lies its <hi>impiety?</hi> This ſeemeth contrary to the general nature of the <hi>Act;</hi> for that is a <hi>Religious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on the Solemn Publick Worſhip of the true God in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> Irregularity and Diſorder may be an iniqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y in the Adminiſtrator; but that the <hi>Attendance on Gods Worſhip diſorderly diſpenſed, is impious in Gods People,</hi> my Bible doth not teach; lend me yours, for I will not perſiſt in any thing that writeth <hi>impiety</hi> on my Soul; my Charity will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to charge them with <hi>impiety,</hi> who voluntarily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Service, only becauſe they do ſo; miſguided Zeal is not alwayes <hi>impious.</hi> I dare not charge our <hi>firſt R for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and <hi>Marian Martyrs,</hi> to have gone to the Stake, under the Guilt, and in the very Act of <hi>impiety?</hi> and yet many of them went embracing, commending, chanting, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their laſt Devotion and Breath, in the <hi>Words,</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Common-Prayer.</hi> Gradual Defect, will not acquit their Act from <hi>impiety;</hi> if it now be, it then was an <hi>Act
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52790:35"/>
impious</hi> to ſerve God by the <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> Our meaſure of increaſed light, and many Obligations, may aggravate our perſiſtance in it, but wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l not alter the <hi>nature</hi> of the Act, in it ſelf <hi>impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us.</hi> Conſcience bindeth me to be preſent in the Solemn Convocation, and perſonally attend his Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the which, when I come to it, is by the impious Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator, diſpenſed in a rude, diſorderly, irreverend Mode, which maketh it my burden, and my Soul to loath, what I dare not leave, becauſe it is for Matter and eſſential Form the Lords Ordinance: Is this an Act <hi>impious?</hi> Let Brethrens <hi>Piety</hi> work by Charity, to evince the <hi>Impiety;</hi> I will give Glory to God, and return; till then, let me proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cenſure.</p>
                  <p>You ſpecifie ſome Sequels of this mine attendance on <hi>Solemn Publick Worſhip,</hi> in this Mode and Order; but they are ſuch, as will not convince the ſame of <hi>impiety;</hi> you ſay,</p>
                  <p>I hereby <hi>weaken Friends,</hi> and <hi>strengthen Enemies:</hi> I pray you how, and wherein? The Friends and Enemies of <hi>Non-Communion</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> from the Engliſh Reformed Church, never came into the Calender of my Friends or Enemies; nor were they ever owned by ſober <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> conteſting for gradual Reformation: If ſuch be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>ſtrengthned, and weakned;</hi> I bleſs God that I have done my Duty, and that my practice doth edifie, whilſt I am not permitted to preach. I muſt confeſs, it is one end of my Action; I account it mine Honour, really to witneſs againſt <hi>Non-communion,</hi> in my very Conflicts for <hi>Reformation:</hi> But if Friends and Enemies to that <hi>Gradual Reformation,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on our age and hands, be <hi>weakned, or ſtrengthned,</hi> it may be mine <hi>Affl ction,</hi> it is not mine <hi>Impiety;</hi> for this Event is by accident, not naturall and genuine; the reſult of weakneſs in the one, and wickedneſs in the other, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not that <hi>Non-conforming Communion,</hi> is an indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty, and eſſential to Church-Reformation. I muſt keep in my houſe if I will cleanſe it, though the filth in it is mine Annoyance: <hi>Circumſtantial Defects,</hi> Redundant Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, and Diſorders, will not warrantably diſcharge mine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52790:36"/>
attendance on the <hi>ſubſtantial, and truly exiſting worſhip of God:</hi> In this Caſe, give me leave to ſay to ſtumbling Friends and Brethren, you have Zeal, but <hi>not according to knowledge.</hi> I muſt by <hi>Union</hi> with the Church, ſeek <hi>Purity</hi> of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and none but wilful Fools, or mad Men, will run to the Channel to drink, becauſe men at Sea are glad to drink ſtinking water, or deny to waſh the Veſſel, or force all for ever to drink in ſuch unclean Veſſels, becauſe ſome through neceſſity can, and do drink in ſuch: And yet Brother, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but tell you, I have the comfort of my own Endeavours, to anticipate this <hi>accidental Event,</hi> by thoſe Papers which I paſſed into the City, with an intent to have paſſed them into the World; in which you have my Apology for this <hi>Act:</hi> And in Anſwer to this Objection, I pray God they who ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their Publication, when they might have done it, may ſeriouſly conſider the ſervice they have done the Church of God; I could do no more to make <hi>even paths to weak feet;</hi> if thoſe who ſhould, would not pave it, I cannot help it; I am innocent of the blood of all men, who ſtumble at this Act (in it ſelf lawful) and indiſpenſably neceſſary, becauſe of thoſe accidents which I have done my part to anticipate.</p>
                  <p>But you ſay, I hereby <hi>undo my good Teſtimony, and give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Cauſe in which I appeared,</hi> This beareth indeed an Aſpect of <hi>Impiety;</hi> an Apoſtate is odious to God and men: I have ever reſolved (and may ere long prove it) to dye, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than do this; my Conſcience beareth me witneſs, <hi>All this is come upon me, yet have I not dealt falſly in the Covenant.</hi> Had this been objected by men who knew not Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who never read the Writings for which he ſuffered, it had been a tolerable miſtake; well may others, when my Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars and Brethren ſo much miſtake my <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> and miſread my <hi>Cauſe;</hi> well might <hi>Thomas Tomkins</hi> confound me with our late Uſurping Traytors, when my <hi>Fellow-Presbyters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found me with Separatiſts. I obſerve you grant my <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> given, is <hi>good;</hi> I wiſh it had been owned with leſs fear and ſhame, I had been then more encouraged in it: But I pray Brother, what was it? Was it the <hi>Cauſe of ſeparation from,</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:52790:36"/>
or <hi>Non-communion</hi> with the Engliſh Reformed Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe corrupt, or Backſlider in its Reformation? Have I been all this time a Martyr for Independency? nothing leſs; <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary Crofton a Separatiſt from,</hi> or <hi>Non-communicant</hi> with a backſliding, corrupt, diſordered Church, is as great, as clear a Contradiction, as <hi>Zachary Crofton a Traytor to King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second:</hi> Which of the people who ſate under my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, will ſay, I now undo the <hi>good Teſtimony I gave,</hi> and <hi>give away the Cauſe for which I appeared?</hi> Do I now practice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than I have preached? Who hath read the Books for which I ſuffer, and will ſay, I, by this Act, <hi>Give away the Cauſe, and undo my good Teſtimony?</hi> Read <hi>my Bonds,</hi> pag. 35. <hi>Whatever ſhall be the eſtabliſhment in the Church, though never ſo corrupt, yet whil'ſt conſiſtent with Salvation, though it may occaſion to me Suffering, and Suſpention of my Miniſtry, by Gods Grace it ſhall not effect in me Schiſm from the Church.</hi> Read <hi>my Fetters,</hi> pag. 49, 50. <hi>This Reformation cannot juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Separation; for that the Corruptions eſtabliſhed, were never made a ſufficient ground for Separation; ſober, ſerious Non-conformiſts, who groaned under the burden of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and for this Reformation, were grieved by, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended againſt this Separation, as that which wanted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground.</hi> Read again <hi>mine Epiſtle</hi> to Mr. <hi>Firmins Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgical Conſiderator,</hi> in pag. 3. <hi>I can keep Communion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Form of Worſhip whereby I cannot Administer; and I can heartily ſay</hi> Amen <hi>to the Matter of thoſe Petitions which are put up in an Order ſo confuſed, prepoſterous, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted; that it ſeemeth to me to be ſo much below the Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, whoſe mouth I muſt be; the Seriouſneſs of the Office whereby I adminiſter, the Sanctity of the Duty I am to perform, and the Sacred Nature of the Object to whom they are preſented, that I dare not ſtand between God and his people with the ſame.</hi> This laſt is part of my Teſtimony concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and againſt the <hi>Lyturgy it ſelf:</hi> Now Sir, What is my <hi>good Teſtimony?</hi> Wherein is it <hi>undone?</hi> Am I not practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in the expreſs ſtate in which I ſtated it? It was ever far from mine intentions to be an <hi>Advocate,</hi> much leſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52790:37"/>
a <hi>Martyr,</hi> for <hi>Non-communion and Separation:</hi> Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Reformation is my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> hath made my <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony;</hi> if I undo, or give away this <hi>Inculca me tanquam ſalem inſipidum.</hi> Good Brother, read me right, and charge me not with <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> who drive with all my main, my <hi>good Teſtimony</hi> againſt the one, as well as the other, extream of Reformation: You wound your ſelves, and engage Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (by your Cenſures) to Clamour, and call me <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:</hi> But you cannot convince me, nor any that know me and <hi>my Teſtimony,</hi> that I am ſtarted one hairs breadth from <hi>my Cauſe;</hi> this condemned practice, is the formal purſuit of my Conteſt; I muſt therefore ſee very good grounds before I give back.</p>
                  <p>Having anſwered your Charge of <hi>Impolicy</hi> and <hi>Impiety,</hi> I muſt conſider your ſuggeſted Arguments againſt <hi>mine atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Gods Solemn Publick Worſhip in this place and order:</hi> And truly Brother, theſe are few and obſcure, I underſtand them not: You ſpeak of <hi>Ordinances, which the Brethren think to be materially corrupt:</hi> I can ſay no more to this, but only to requeſt they will ſpeak out their thoughts, and ſpecifie the <hi>ſeeming corrupt matter,</hi> and then I will judge concerning it: And when they come to do this, I think they will find, <hi>Secundae Cogitationes ſunt meliores;</hi> they will find it is the <hi>Mode,</hi> not <hi>Matter,</hi> that is corrupt. You ſay, <hi>The Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Doctrine, and Worſhip of Prayer, ſeemeth not only to be the</hi> objectum ad quem (I think <hi>quod</hi> more proper) <hi>but</hi> pro quibus; <hi>whether things or perſons, wherein they take it for granted the Common-Prayer is corrupt.</hi> This I profeſs I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not; What do you mean by the <hi>Matter of Doctrine, and Worſhip of Prayer?</hi> Are theſe terms Synonimous? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you by them <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſuggeſted in, and by <hi>Prayer?</hi> Or the <hi>Credentials of the Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> diſtinct from the Worſhip of Praye? I pray you explain yourſelf, and then know, <hi>Think ſo, Seemeth ſo;</hi> and <hi>take for granted,</hi> may be ſuppoſed grounds for your <hi>Cenſures;</hi> but ſignifie nothing to my <hi>Conviction;</hi> which muſt be on certainty if it ſuperſede,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52790:37"/>
what I conclude indiſpenſable Duty: Indeed your annexed inſtance maketh me think, you mean the <hi>Matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſuggeſted by Prayer;</hi> for you ſpecifie <hi>Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, as a ſuperiour Degree of Ministry;</hi> and if ſo, you will give me leave to tell you, you have antidated your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; for our Books pray for none but <hi>Biſhops and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> or <hi>Paſtors and Curates;</hi> ſo that till the time of change come, I may (notwithſtanding this Exception) continue my Communion; when the new Book cometh, I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the weight of this Plea; in the mean time I pray you reſolve me, <hi>Will ſingle Errours preached,</hi> much leſs ſuggeſted in Prayer, <hi>warrant Non-communion with a true Church, Non-attendance on Goſpel-Miniſtry, and Gods Solemn Publick Worſhip?</hi> What meaneth, when bindeth that Rule of our Redeemer, <hi>Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees?</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand by <hi>take heed what you he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r?</hi> hear not them <hi>who teach for Doctrines the Traditions of men.</hi> May not a perſonal Diſſent be entered to a Petition, for a miſtaken Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ſuggeſting an Errour as its Baſis? Or muſt the whole Prayer for <hi>Matter</hi> generally good, therefore be diſowned? This will neceſſitate, and was the firſt cauſe of <hi>S t-forms of Prayer,</hi> and require that they <hi>compoſed,</hi> be not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated <hi>fratr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bus doctioribus;</hi> but alſo to every <hi>indiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Member of the Church,</hi> who muſt join in Prayer; and ſo Sir, we fight well, to flie upon, by flying from a Common-Prayer Book.</p>
                  <p>You add, The Brethren think mine attendance on it is <hi>aequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> if not <hi>aqualiter; As if I ſhould read or adminiſter by this Form; and that there can be no Obligation of Duty, or Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation warranting the one, which may not alſo juſtifie the other.</hi> To this I ſay, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nk ſo</hi> will not convince; but of ſuch who thus think, I would enquire, Is the common ſtate of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, different from the ſpecial ſtate of a Miniſter? And ſo the Capacities, Duties, and Obligations of each different; ſo that the one may be <hi>continued,</hi> while the other doth <hi>ceaſe.</hi> The one may, and muſt be <hi>acted,</hi> when the other is <hi>arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:52790:38"/>
ſuperſeded, or violently barred; if men of power in the Church will <hi>diſcapacitate me for the one,</hi> doth it <hi>ipſo facto, diſcharge me from the other?</hi> Do our diſcapacitated Common Councel-men ceaſe to be <hi>Citizens?</hi> Or be they not bound to retain their Relation, and participate or communicate in the common good of the City, under what (they judge to be) the rude and diſordered Government thereof? I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Obligation of my <hi>Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> to be <hi>aeque,</hi> or <hi>aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter,</hi> neceſſitous and extenſive with that of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> I muſt be, and act as a <hi>Christian,</hi> when thoſe conditions are required from me which I cannot yield, and without which I may not be permitted to act as a <hi>Miniſter;</hi> and thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions will not diſcharge the Duties of the one, nor bar the Exerciſe of them which do bar the other. I a Miniſter, ſtand in a <hi>general</hi> and <hi>ſpecial</hi> Relation to the Church, and am charged with Duties proper and peculiar to each of theſe. I may be ſinfully impoſed on, and reſtrained from my <hi>special,</hi> by thoſe things which will not bar the Duties of my <hi>general Relation</hi> and Capacity: I conceive <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of Gods Worſhip, is much different from <hi>Attendance</hi> on Gods Worſhip; and I ſtand bound to the laſt, when I am (juſtly or unjuſtly) barred from the firſt. <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Prieſts,</hi> were not barred from ſerving God with the Church, when thruſt from ſerving in the Prieſts Office. In my <hi>general Relation, as a Member of the Church,</hi> I ſtand charged, and am capacitated to judge the <hi>Matter, and eſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Form of Gods Worſhip;</hi> aſſent to which, is mine only Act: But in my <hi>ſpecial Relation, as a Miniſter,</hi> I ſtand alſo charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and am capacitated to judge the <hi>Miniſterial Mode,</hi> and humane Order by which Gods Worſhip is celebrated; and if herein I be impoſed on, and that by an Order rude, irreverend, and unſutable to God, his Church, or Worſhip; which right Reaſon, much leſs true Religion, will not allow me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; I am interrupted in my <hi>Miniſterial Office,</hi> the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of which is, <hi>As a man to Modifie Gods Inſtitutions,</hi> whereby an intercourſe is maintained between God and men; ſuch impoſition I judge to be a ſubverſion of <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52790:38"/>
Office and Authority;</hi> not to be offered by others, or admitted by my ſelf, without great iniquity; and if it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be enforced by violence, that I muſt be reſtrained from my <hi>Miniſterial Modification of Gods Ordinances</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mine Office, and Miniſterial Gifts received; or I may not be permitted to Miniſter, I yet ſtand in my Relation, as a <hi>Member of the Church,</hi> bound to communicate: The <hi>Miniſterial Mode impoſed,</hi> and <hi>ſinfully received</hi> (by ſuch as ſubjugate their Miniſtry) not <hi>vitiating the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> or nullifying the Ordinances of God; will not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant my Non-attendance on them: It is not equally neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and obliging, that I a Speaker, pronounce a wild in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted Speech, full of Incongruities, Non-ſenſe, and Soleciſms (from which a ſound mind doth bar me) as that I join and concur in the Subſtantials thereof with the Aſſemblies, ſo asking common and certain good things.</p>
                  <p>I may not caſt off my general Relation, wherein I am <hi>purely paſſive,</hi> becauſe thoſe things are to be perſonally acted in my ſpecial Relation and Capacity, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without ſin conſent to do, and therefore muſt ſtand ſtill. I cannot beat it into my Brains, that it is <hi>aeque,</hi> or <hi>aequaliter</hi> to attend, and give an Aſſent unto the <hi>Matter prayed,</hi> as to utter, pronounce, and expreſs the <hi>raw, rude, and diſorderly Speech of the Speaker:</hi> Or that the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> or <hi>Obligation</hi> of the whole Houſe, in this general Order to preſent it ſelf before his Majeſty, which will and doth warrant the one, may juſtifie the other; the Speakers Speech is often cenſured, when the Commons concerned in it are commended and juſtified.</p>
                  <p>But Sir, Rather than not enforce this Fancy, you will knock me on the Head with a <hi>Chamber-pot;</hi> you urge my neceſſity to Communion, to be the ſame to Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tell me, <hi>I judge the Nurſe is bound in Duty and Neceſſity to give the Child his bread</hi> (his milk had
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52790:39"/>
been more proper) <hi>out of a Chamber-pot, as ſhe her ſelf; or the Child it ſelf out of it:</hi> An homely Simile, but in a <hi>ſtarving Neceſſity,</hi> I do judge ſo; but I judge Similes do not <hi>currere quatuor pedibus,</hi> there is no aptitude in this to my Caſe, that Neceſſity will conſtrain me to take my Meat in an unclean Veſſel; which will not conſtrain me to give it in that Veſſel to another. I ſuppoſe your Nurſe is poor, who hath no other Veſſel but a <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-pot;</hi> yet I muſt ſuppoſe her a good Huſwife capacita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make it <hi>clean:</hi> But if her Superiours have ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped her of all other, and will bar her from her clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this, I ſuppoſe ſhe is not bound to play the Nurſe, and feed others, though ſhe muſt thus feed her ſelf; if filthy Parents will have ſuch Nurſes, or none, I hope it is in my power to be none of them, I am not bound to it, I am by Nature bound to deny it; and yet I muſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mine own <hi>being</hi> as well as I can: If the <hi>being of Chriſtianity</hi> depend upon my <hi>perſonal Ministry,</hi> as my <hi>being,</hi> or <hi>appearing a Chriſtian,</hi> doth on my <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church viſible, your Inference might be of ſome force, but this it doth not: That therefore you may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the difference, keep to ſimilitudes more apt: The King hath Decreed, All the Citizens ſhall each Month preſent their Petitions by a joint Aſſent to the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a Speaker; the Governours of this City direct a courſe by which to deſign different Speakers, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <hi>Matter</hi> to be ſpoken, and the <hi>Mode</hi> of ſpeaking; the firſt is <hi>good, and allowed;</hi> the ſecond is <hi>rude, and diſordered;</hi> the Speakers can better expreſs the deſired Matter, but ſhall not be permitted; are they <hi>aeque,</hi> or <hi>aequaliter,</hi> ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iged to ſpeak in this <hi>Mode,</hi> as to attend this Aſſembly, and give Aſſent to this common good <hi>Matter</hi> rudely expreſſed by others? Not ſpeaking in this <hi>Mode,</hi> they loſe the Honour and Advantages of the Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but not attending, or aſſenting to the Matter, they loſe the benefit and being of Citizens; are theſe equally to be embraced and purſued? They are bound in the one
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52790:39"/>
perſonally to <hi>Act,</hi> and denying to ſubjugate their <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um rationale,</hi> to the rude Preſcriptions of others, they are barred from it; but reſolved into the common ſtate, in which, <hi>aſſent to the Matter</hi> is their only Act, being wholly and purely paſſive in the preſcribed and impoſed Form and Mode of expreſſion; in your <hi>Chamber-pot</hi> Caſe, you ſuppoſe <hi>Christianity</hi> to depend on my <hi>perſonal Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> (which my Relation as a Nurſe doth renounce) and then indeed your Inference may be cogent; for then your <hi>Chamber-pot</hi> will ſquare with <hi>du Moulins, Fools Coat;</hi> but in my more ſutable and ſociable Caſe, I am bound to <hi>attendance</hi> when, and where I am not bound to <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter:</hi> The Neceſſity of City-Intereſt and Relation, doth bind me to <hi>attendance,</hi> and <hi>aſſent to City-Petitions;</hi> but not to the Duty and Dignity of a Speaker, between the King and the City, from which I am barred by the <hi>irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional impoſition</hi> of an <hi>irregular, undue Mode of expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in which I muſt perſonally act, by a ſuſpenſe of my <hi>Judicium rationale,</hi> which I am bound to act in this more, and beyond what I muſt judge in my more common Capacity.</p>
                  <p>Now Sir, I muſt tell you, I know not whom you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by the Brethren, who are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the reſt; ſure I am, they are not <hi>Congregationalliſts,</hi> who have no little blaſphemed the <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENANT,</hi> by their late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions for it, and by their <hi>Martyrs</hi> pretences to it, as the Bond of their moſt barbarous, pernitious Treaſons and Impieties; which was by themſelves ſlighted as an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack out of Date,</hi> and prophanely, blaſphemouſly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated before they could, or did conſult and perpetrate the ſame: I cannot ſuppoſe them to be the Brethren, for the late <hi>ſpecifical Difference,</hi> whoſe Policy propounded an interpretation of the <hi>COVENANT,</hi> contrary to the literal ſenſe, and Grammatical Conſtruction thereof; from whom, and which you know, I was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; it hath been mine unhappineſs, that few of the Brethren
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52790:40"/>
have been <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the preſent concernments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; nor could I expect it, whilſt I could not be heard to ſpeak; nor was worth reading when I had written.</p>
                  <p>Again, I muſt tell you that it is my Grief to obſerve that many are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Negatives,</hi> who are, and are reſolved to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Poſitives:</hi> Theſe agree with me in, and againſt the Diſorders which ſhould <hi>not be,</hi> but diſſent from me in that Order which <hi>ſhould be in the Church:</hi> They conſent, when I ſay, <hi>Miniſters muſt not conform;</hi> but underſtand me not, or affirm me Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, when I ſay, <hi>Members muſt communicate.</hi> They own me as <hi>Zealous,</hi> when I cry to the ſons of <hi>Eli, You do wickedly, thus rudely to Adminiſter;</hi> but diſown me as impious, when I tell <hi>Iſrael, You muſt bring your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to the Lord, though by reaſon of the profane Prieſts, and rude Adminiſtration thereof, your Soul doth loath them.</hi> They like me well, and cry me up, when I ſay, <hi>The Image of Jealouſie provoketh God, and hath brought him down from his Mercy-ſeat, to the Threſhold of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> but look a ſquint, and cry down, when I tell them, <hi>I will follow, not go before God; Iſrael muſt know, and appear in the Temple as Gods houſe, though he be at the Threſhold ready to depart, but not yet gone.</hi> How long ſhall we repreſent the Spirit of <hi>Reformation,</hi> to be a Spirit of <hi>Contradiction?</hi> and verifie that odious Scandal, <hi>That Non-conformiſts condemn every thing, but cannot tell what they would have.</hi> I have obſerved new light is <hi>only reprehenſive,</hi> but true light is alſo <hi>diſcretive</hi> and <hi>directive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Good Brother, Deſire ſuch who in this are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to caſt an eye on that Tract (almoſt loſt in our late Confuſions) which <hi>Cartwright, Geree, Hilderſham, Dod, Ball, Hind, Nicholls, Langley,</hi> did tread out, between the <hi>Conformity</hi> thou (as now) required; and the <hi>Non-communion</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:52790:40"/>
by the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and <hi>Semiſeparatiſts</hi> then as now preſſed, practiſed, and conteſted for, with more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling Cenſures, than convincing Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh all thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Brethren, would ſeriouſly ſtudy the Nature of <hi>Separation and Non-communion,</hi> and obſerve the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>quantity of Corruptions,</hi> which all who have written on that Subject, have concluded may be in a Church, before they conſtitute a <hi>warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cauſe of Separation, or Non-communion.</hi> I have not met with any who would not allow, yea, require Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion as a Duty with a Church whoſe Miniſters are <hi>vile,</hi> Members <hi>wicked,</hi> Miniſtration <hi>rude and diſorderly,</hi> Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures <hi>wanting,</hi> or <hi>warding againſt the power of Godlineſs;</hi> Worſhip <hi>polluted,</hi> and in which <hi>Idolatry</hi> is practiſed, but conjunct with Gods true Worſhip; their Altars ſtanding by Gods <hi>Altar;</hi> their Poſt by <hi>his Poſt;</hi> their Groves and high Places, <hi>in his holy Mountain, near unto his very Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> I will not in theſe Caſes except <hi>Cotton,</hi> or <hi>H oker;</hi> by whoſe Principles (the being of the Church admitted) I will be bound to defend my preſent Practice.</p>
                  <p>Good Brother, Remember, Conſider our difference from the former ſtate of theſe holy men is <hi>Gradual,</hi> not <hi>Real;</hi> the <hi>Duty</hi> or <hi>Impiety</hi> was in nature the ſame to them, the meaſure and aggravation is more to us: They indeed acted beyond what I can allow, and in what I can better excuſe, than juſtifie them; but their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Communion, are armed with Religious Reaſon, beyond what can be reſiſted.</p>
                  <p>If now, <hi>I am left alone</hi> (for I muſt yet proceed) I ſhall only note <hi>paucity of Profeſſors,</hi> is attendant on all <hi>Criticiſms</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſtrait is the Gate. <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> muſt follow God <hi>throughly, not turning to the right or left hand.</hi> Gods Worſhip, diſorder'd in its <hi>Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Mode,</hi> I attend with Grief; but the <hi>Corruptions</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:52790:41"/>
being <hi>extrinſecal, not vitiating the Subject,</hi> under which Gods Worſhip is for <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>conſtitutive Form</hi> his own, I dare not leave it, I dare not but attend it; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reſtraint removed, I have no ground of Faith in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect hereof, to expect <hi>ſpecial Grace</hi> or Preſence; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with Confidence appeal to God, with <hi>Lord, Thou wilt have Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cy, not Sacrifice.</hi> As a common Chriſtian, I am charged to <hi>judge the Matter;</hi> as a Miniſter, the <hi>Mode</hi> and <hi>Order of Gods Worſhip;</hi> when it is convincingly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, that theſe two are <hi>aeque,</hi> or <hi>aequaliter, neceſſitous</hi> and <hi>obliging,</hi> I ſhall either <hi>Conform,</hi> or ceaſe to <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate;</hi> till then, I pray you Brethren, receive my Practice as a Comment on my <hi>Cauſe and Teſtimony;</hi> and give me leave without your Cenſures (provoking, juſtifying the Clamours of the wicked) to walk with my God in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his Church viſible, conform to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Dictates of my Conſcience;</hi> This is the Deſire of, Sir,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Brother, Conſtant to God, And his Covenant. <hi>ZACHARY CROFTON.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
